ShinY
深影
深影字幕组原创译制
深影字幕组论坛
http://shinybbs.com
翻译 RT1
翻译 Roshan
翻译 伴我梦
翻译 POPPINS
翻译 哈哈哈
翻译 莫离酱
特效 烟斗oo0
后期 小滔
校对 神探小海豚
总监 柒一四
神探夏洛克
前情提要
年
夏洛克
福尔摩斯
在另一个时空
年
神探夏洛克
◆◆◆
◆◆\h ◆
\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h本尼迪克特·康伯巴奇
马丁·弗瑞曼
\h\h\h\h\h\h编剧&主创
\h马克·加蒂斯
\h史蒂文·莫法特
斯特兰德杂志
改编自阿瑟·柯南·道尔的原著
制片人
\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h苏·维特
导演
\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h格拉斯·麦金农
贝克街.西
斯彼得威尔茶餐厅
可恶的新娘
速来
马夫称"就是瑞克莱蒂夫人"
西区恐怖杀人案
贵族惨遭杀害
伊斯灵顿小教堂
惊现船长尸体
鬼魂身份未定
马夫称"就是瑞克莱蒂夫人"
恶棍"新娘"杀人案
下一个受害者是谁
伦敦警察厅感到困惑
汉莫斯诺子爵神秘死亡
约翰·华生医生
m 0 0 l 0 289 l 5 289 l 5 0 l 0 0
\h 若方便 速来
若不方便
也请速来
福尔摩斯
第欧根尼俱乐部
第
欧
根
尼
俱
乐
部
请
保
持
安
静
请保持安静
早上好  怀尔德
我哥哥在吗
当然 先生 他在吃早餐
现在是早餐时间
他在贵宾室吗
是的  先生
这位先生是我的客人
是吗
是华生医生吧
我很喜欢您写的《蓝宝石奇案》  先生
谢谢
很高兴你能喜欢
你长得
非常  丑
您说什么
我说很丑
您刚才说到《蓝色的鱼贩》
真是太丑
很高兴你喜欢我的土豆
你得多加练习 华生
你花太多时间去
舞蹈课了
想我了吗
新娘在玻璃中的倒影
目击者
新娘
马夫称 马夫称 马夫称 马夫称
"就是瑞克莱蒂夫人"
又一个愤怒的新娘
鬼魂身份未定
马夫称"就是瑞克莱蒂夫人"
鬼魂新娘之谜
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
挚爱的姐妹
忠诚至死不渝
卒于1984年12月18日 享年26岁
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
挚爱的姐妹
忠诚至死不渝
卒于1984年12月18日 享年26岁
红胡子
斯彼得威尔茶餐厅
旺兹沃思 英国英格兰东南部城市
也有强制婚姻的意思
fall有瀑布和坠落的含义
希腊神话中 复仇女神追捕并惩罚犯下罪行的人
只要世上有罪恶 她们就必然存在
我叫夏洛克·福尔摩斯 住在贝克街221B号
The name's Sherlock Holmes and the address is 221B Baker Street.
- 午安 - 好的
- Afternoon. - Yeah.
他一直就这样
He's always like that.
今天过得不好吗
Bad day was it?
你昨天才搬进来和他住
Since yesterday you've moved in
现在你们就一起破案了
with him and now you're solving crimes together.
瞧你这副开心的模样 真不像样
Mwah! Look at you, all happy, it's not decent.
谁在意像不像样 哈德森夫人 游戏开始了
Who cares about decent? The game, Mrs. Hudson, is on!
别把人想成英雄 约翰
Don't make people into heroes, John.
英雄并不存在 即使存在 我也不在其中
Heroes don't exist and, if they did, I wouldn't be one of them.
我会让你生不如死
I will burn the heart out of you.
这样应该就行了
Right, this should do it.
- 你穿裤子了吗 - 没有
- Are you wearing any pants? - No.
好吧
Ok.
我想让你记住 我打你的样子
This is how I want you to remember me, the woman who beat you.
但是怪物并不存在
But there never was any monster.
夏洛克 我们总算见面了
Sherlock? Here we are, at last.
- 永别了 约翰 - 夏洛克
- Goodbye, John. - Sherlock!
"那些东西会害死你"
'Those things will kill you.'
你这个混球
Oh, you bastard!
追寻罪犯的快感 令人血脉喷张
The thrill of the chase, the blood pumping through your veins,
我们两人对阵整个世界
just the two of us against the rest of the world.
等等
Wait!
我们需要相互配合
We're going to need to coordinate.
我求你再次创造奇迹
I asked you for one more miracle.
- 我求你不要死 - 我知道了
- I asked you to stop being dead. - I heard you.
闭嘴 你不是解谜者 你一直都不是
Shut up! You are not a puzzle solver, you never have been.
你就是个喜剧女王
You're a drama queen!
现在有人快要死了
Now there is a man in there about to die.
游戏开始了 你快解密啊
The game is on, solve it!
他就是敲诈界的拿破仑
He is the Napoleon of blackmail.
这次你不能成为英雄了 福尔摩斯先生
No chance for you to be a hero this time, Mr. Holmes.
我是一个高智商的反社会分子
I'm a high-functioning sociopath!
不管把夏洛克关到什么监狱里
There is no prison in which we could incarcerate Sherlock without
他每天都能引起骚动
causing a riot on a daily basis.
我们还有另一个方案 但需要您的批准
The alternative, however, would require your approval.
致我们最美好的时光 约翰
To the very best of times, John.
你想我了吗
Did you miss me?
这怎么可能
How is this possible?
- 被流放的滋味如何 - 我才刚离开四分钟
- How is the exile going? - I've only been gone four minutes.
我希望 你已经吸取教训了
Well, I certainly hope you've learnt your lesson.
这次是谁 需要我的帮助
Who needs me this time?
你想我吗
Miss me?
英国
England.
"第二次阿富汗战争 给很多人
"The Second Afghan War brought
带来了荣誉和晋升的机会
honours and promotion to many.
但对我来说 这只是一场不幸和灾难"
But, for me, it meant nothing but misfortune and disaster."
没事了 上尉
All right, Captain.
"我拖着毁坏的身体 回到了英国
"I returned to England with my health irretrievably ruined
我的前途一片渺茫
And my future bleak.
在这种情况下
Under such circumstances,
我自然而然地 被吸引到了伦敦
I naturally gravitated to London.
伦敦这个污水坑里 集聚了国内所有..."
That great cesspool into which all the loungers..."
- 华生 - "游手好闲的懒汉"
- Watson! - "And idlers of the empire are drained."
华生
Watson!
我是斯坦福德
Stamford.
还记得我吗
Remember?
我们在圣巴特医院共事过
We were at Barts together.
我当然记得 你是斯坦福德
Yes, of course. Stamford.
我的天 你去哪里了
Good Lord! Where have you been?
你现在骨瘦如柴的
You're as thin as a rake!
我顺利回家了 很多人牺牲在了战场上
I made it home. Many weren't so lucky.
- 你现在怎么样 - 我需要找一个住处
- So what now? - I need a place to live.
一个体面 我又能承担的地方 并不容易找到
Somewhere decent at an affordable price. It's not easy.
今天你是第二个 跟我说这话的人
You know, you're the second person to say that to me today.
第一个人是谁
Hmm? Who was the first?
我的天啊
Good Lord.
看来他在做实验
It's an experiment, apparently.
他鞭挞尸体是为了证明
Beating corpses to establish
死后的淤青能存在多长时间
how long after death bruising is still possible.
从医学角度看 他这样做有什么意义吗
Is there a medical point to that?
我不知道
Not sure.
我也不知道 你的朋友在哪里
Neither am I. So, where's this friend of yours, then?
打扰了
Excuse me.
希望我们没有打扰到你
I do hope we're not interrupting.
我觉得你去过阿富汗
You've been in Afghanistan, I perceive.
华生医生 这位是夏洛克先生...
Dr. Watson, Mr. Sherlock...
优秀的反应能力 你是个不错的人选
Excellent reflexes, you'll do.
抱歉 您说什么
I'm sorry...?
我看中了摄政公园附近的一间套房
I have my eye on a suite of rooms near Regent's Park.
我们俩一起 可以承担房租
Between us we could afford them.
租房 我们没提过租房的事情啊
Rooms? Who said anything about rooms?
今早我提过此事
I did, I mentioned it this morning,
我需要一名同住的房客
I was in need of a fellow lodger.
午饭后 斯坦福德就出现在这里
Now he appears after lunch
还带着一名参过军的男子
in the company of a man of military aspect
你黝黑的皮肤 和近期的伤病表明
with a tan and a recent injury, both suggestive
你参加过阿富汗战役 并被迫离开战场
of the campaign in Afghanistan and an enforced departure from it.
结论自然就出来了
The conclusion seemed inescapable.
明晚 我们再敲定细节
We'll finalise the details tomorrow evening.
我先失陪了
Now, if you'll excuse me,
在旺兹沃思有场绞刑
I have a hanging in
我不喜欢他们在我没到之前开场
Wandsworth and I'd hate them to start without me.
- 绞刑 - 这是我的职业兴趣
- A hanging? - I take a professional interest.
我还喜欢拉小提琴和抽烟斗
I also play the violin and smoke a pipe.
你应该不会介意吧
I presume that's not a problem.
不会
Er, no, well...
而且很明显 你习惯不把话说完
And you're clearly acclimatized to never getting
我们会相处得很好
to the end of a sentence. We'll get along splendidly.
那我们明晚七点见
Tomorrow evening, seven o'clock, then.
对了 我叫夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Oh, and the name is Sherlock Holmes
套房地址是贝克街221B号
and the address is 221B, Baker Street.
他一直是这副样子
Yes... he's always been like that.
报纸 卖报纸
Papers! Papers!
- "蓝宝石奇案" 卖得好吗 - 非常好 华生医生
- Here, how's The Blue Carbuncle doing? - Very popular, Dr. Watson.
下个月还会有正式的谋杀案吗
Is there going to be a proper murder next month?
我会去找警察和罪犯谈谈
I'll have a word with the criminal classes.
如果您不介意
If you wouldn't mind.
是他吗 他在车里吗
Is that him? Is he in there?
不
Ow! No.
不 他不在 祝您过得愉快 再见
No, no, not at all. Er, good day to you.
启程吧
Let on, walk.
圣诞节快乐 福尔摩斯先生
Merry Christmas, Mr. Holmes!
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
我希望您计划要回家之时 能通知我一声
I do wish you'd let me know when you're planning to come home!
我自己都不清楚呢 哈德森夫人
I hardly knew myself, Mrs. Hudson.
那些被肢解的乡绅是个麻烦事
That's the trouble with dismembered country squires.
众所周知 他们的时间很难安排
They're notoriously difficult to schedule.
- 箱子里面是什么 - 没什么
- What's in there? - Never mind.
谢谢
Thank you.
你抓住凶手了吗 福尔摩斯先生
Did you catch the murderer, Mr. Holmes?
抓住凶手了 但还在找乡绅们的腿
Caught the murderer, still looking for the legs.
我们算是打成平手了吧
I think we'll call it a draw.
我注意到
And I noticed you've
你又发表了一个故事 华生医生
published another of your stories, Dr. Watson.
- 是的 你喜欢那个故事吗 - 不
- Yes, did you enjoy it? - No.
- 我一直不喜欢那些故事 - 为什么不喜欢呢
- I never enjoy them. - Why not?
我从来都没台词 对不对
Well, I never say anything, do I?
在你笔下
According to you, I just show
我只负责带人上楼 还有给你们送早餐
people up the stairs and serve you breakfasts.
在故事里
Well, within the narrative,
总得来说 那是你的职能
that is, broadly speaking, your function.
我的什么
My what?!
别觉得被针对了 哈德森夫人
Don't feel singled out, Mrs. Hudson,
我在狗的那篇故事里 几乎没说话
I'm hardly in the dog one.
"狗的那篇故事"
"The dog one?"
我是你们的女房东 不是一个情节设定
I'm your landlady, not a plot device.
你是指 "巴斯克维尔的猎犬"那个故事吗
Do you mean The Hound Of The Baskervilles?
你们还把套房弄得又暗又脏
And you make the rooms so drab and dingy.
怪插画家去吧 他才完全失控了
Oh, blame it on the illustrator, he's out of control!
我还得留这种胡子 好让大家认出我来
I've had to grow this moustache just so people will recognise me.
"这么多年来 我很荣幸可以记录
"Over the many years it has been my privilege to record
我了不起的朋友 夏洛克·福尔摩斯的成就
The exploits of my remarkable friend, Mr. Sherlock Holmes,
有时在他众多的案件中 我很难
It has sometimes been difficult to choose which of his many
找出能呈献给读者的故事
Cases to set before my readers.
有些案件太敏感 无法详细描述
Some are still too sensitive to recount,
而有些 则尚存于公众的脑海中
Whilst others are too recent in the minds of the public.
但在我们一起经历的 众多冒险之中
But in all our many adventures together,
还没有哪件案子
no case pushed my friend
像 '可恶的新娘' 那样
To such mental and physical extremes
把我朋友心理 及生理承受力逼到极限"
As that of The Abominable Bride!"
我的天啊
Good Lord!
哈德森夫人 我的客厅里怎么有位女士
Mrs. Hudson, there is a woman in my sitting room!
是你故意安排的吗
Is it intentional?
她是客户 我说你出去了 但她坚持要等你回来
She's a client. Said you were out, insisted on waiting.
您愿意坐下吗
Would you, er, care to sit down?
您问她来做什么了吗
Didn't you ask her what she wanted?
你自己问她啊
You ask her!
你怎么不问她呢
Why didn't YOU ask her?
我怎么问 我都不能说话
How could I, what with me not talking and everything?!
看在上帝的份上 给她加些台词吧
Oh, for God's sake, give her some lines,
她完全可以饿死我们
she's perfectly capable of starving us!
中午好 我是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Good afternoon. I am Sherlock Holmes,
这是我的朋友兼同事 华生医生
this is my friend and colleague, Dr. Watson.
您可以在他面前畅所欲言
You may speak freely in front of him,
- 因为基本上他都听不懂 - 福尔摩斯
- as he rarely understands a word. - Holmes!
然而 在您开口之前
However, before you do,
请允许我进行一些微小的观察
allow me to make some trifling observations.
您调皮而富有幽默感
You have an impish sense of humour,
您现在正用这种幽默感
which currently you are
来减轻自己的痛苦
deploying to ease a degree of personal anguish.
您不久前嫁给
You have recently married
一个表面上性情温和的男人
a man of a seemingly kindly disposition,
而他为了一个讨厌
who has now abandoned you
而且可疑的同伴抛下了你
for an unsavoury companion of dubious morals.
您抱着和解的希望
You have come to this agency as a last resort,
万不得已来到这里
in the hope that reconciliation may still be possible.
我的天啊 福尔摩斯
Good Lord, Holmes!
这些都是从您的香水味 推断出来的
All of this is, of course, perfectly evident from your perfume.
她身上的香水味吗
Her perfume?
是的 我从香水味上能得到推理
Yes, her perfume, which brings insight to me
而你却要面临灾难了
and disaster to you.
你为何这么说
How so?
因为我认出她了 而你却没有
Because I recognised it and you did not.
- 玛丽 - 约翰
- Mary! - John.
天啊 你为什么扮成客户
Why, in God's name, are you pretending to be a client?
因为我想来见自己的丈夫 丈夫
Because I could think of no other way to see my husband, husband.
那件案子是个国际阴谋
It was an affair of international intrigue.
那只是个乡绅谋杀案罢了
It was a murdered country squire.
尽管如此 当时情况很紧急
Nevertheless, matters were pressing.
我不介意你去查案 亲爱的
I don't mind you going, my darling,
我介意的是 你就这样抛下了我
I mind you leaving me behind.
你能帮上什么忙呢
But what could you do?!
那你又帮了什么忙
Well, what do you do,
你不就是一脸惊讶 四处闲逛 记记笔记吗
except wander around taking notes, looking surprised?!
够了
Enough!
舞台已经备好 帷幕已经升起
The stage is set, the curtain rises.
我们要准备开始演出了
We are ready to begin.
开始什么演出
Begin what?
有时若想查明一桩案子 另一桩必先水落石出
Sometimes to solve a case, one must first solve another.
- 你又接新案子了吗 - 是一桩很古老的旧案
- Oh, you have a case, then, a new one? - An old one, very old.
我必须深入调查
I shall have to go deep.
深入调查什么
Deep? Into what?
自身
Myself.
莱斯特雷德 别在门口闲逛了 进来吧
Lestrade! Do stop loitering by the door and come in.
你怎么知道是我
How did you know it was me?
脚步声是无法改变的
The regulation tread is unmistakable.
你的脚步声比琼斯的轻 但比格雷格森的重
Lighter than Jones, heavier than Gregson.
我刚上来 哈德森夫人似乎不愿说话
I... I just came up... Mrs. Hudson didn't seem to be talking.
恐怕她属于
I fear she has branched
用讽刺手法 批判文学作品的流派
into literary criticism by means of satire.
这是当代女房东的趋势 真令人沮丧
It is a distressing trend in the modern landlady.
你为何在下班后过来
What brings you here in your off-duty hours?
- 你怎么知道我下班了 - 自我们开始谈话
- How do you know I'm off duty? - Well, since your arrival,
百分之四十以上的时间 你的眼睛都瞟向酒瓶
you've addressed over 40% of your remarks to my decanter.
华生 把探长明显想要的东西给他吧
Watson, give the Inspector what he so clearly wants.
那么 莱斯特雷德 我们能为你做些什么
So... Lestrade, what can we do for you?
我不是来办事的 我就是顺便来看看
Oh, I'm not here on business, I just thought I'd drop by.
您是指 社交拜访吗
A social call?
是的 我只是来恭贺佳节的
Yeah, of course, just to wish you the compliments of the season.
- 圣诞快乐 - 圣诞快乐
- Merry Christmas. - Merry Christmas.
寒暄总算结束了
Thank God that's over.
探长 什么奇怪的事情逼着你
Now, Inspector, what strange happening compels you
来我这里 但你又难以启齿呢
to my door, but embarrasses you to relate?
我没说有事发生啊
Who said anything happened?
你说了 你想方设法地表现出来了
You did. By every means short of actual speech.
福尔摩斯 你推断错了
Ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, Holmes, you have misdiagnosed.
那么纠正我吧 医生
Then, correct me, Doctor.
他不是想喝酒 他是需要喝酒
He didn't WANT a drink, he needed one.
他不是觉得尴尬 而是感到害怕
He's not embarrassed, he's afraid.
我的传记者学得很快嘛
My Boswell is learning.
他们真是在飞速成长啊
They do grow up so fast.
华生 让伦敦警察厅重拾勇气吧
Watson, restore the courage of Scotland Yard.
探长 请坐下
Inspector, do sit down.
我 我不是在害怕 完全不是
I'm, I'm not afraid, exactly.
恐惧 是面临危险时的一种智慧
Fear is wisdom in the face of danger,
这没有什么好羞耻的
it is nothing to be ashamed of.
谢谢
Thank you.
那就从头开始 讲这个案子吧
From the beginning, then.
是你
You!
不要 求求你
No, please!
是你吗
You?!
等等
A moment.
什么时候发生的事情
When was this?
昨天早上
Yesterday morning.
新娘的脸是什么样的
The bride's face, how was it described?
"死人般惨白 嘴巴像道深红色的伤口"
"White as death, mouth like a crimson wound."
诗意描写 还是真相如此
Poetry or truth?
很多人认为 这两种方式都一样
Many would say they're the same thing.
对 因为他们都是笨蛋
Yes, idiots.
诗意描写 还是真相如此
Poetry or truth?
事发之后 我亲自查看过她的脸
I saw her face myself. Afterwards.
什么事发之后
After what?
是你
You?
还是我
Or me?
莱斯特雷德 一个女人当众吞枪自杀
Oh, really, Lestrade, a woman blows her own brains out in public
你还要我帮忙识别罪犯
and you need help identifying the guilty party?
伦敦警察厅的智商再创新低
I feel Scotland Yard has reached a new low.
这不是我来这里的原因
That's not why I'm here.
- 我猜也是 - 那个新娘 叫什么
- I surmised. - What was her name, the bride?
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂 昨天是她的结婚纪念日
Emelia Ricoletti. Yesterday was her wedding anniversary.
当然 有人报了警
The police, of course, were called.
她的尸体 也被送去了停尸房
And her body taken to the morgue.
这是标准程序 你究竟为何告诉我们此事
Standard procedure. Why are you telling us what may be presumed?
是因为后来 发生了奇怪的事
Because of what happened next.
几个小时之后 在莱姆豪斯
Limehouse. Just a few hours later.
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂的丈夫托马斯·瑞克莱蒂
Thomas Ricoletti. Emelia Ricoletti's husband.
我推断 他是要去停尸房 辨认妻子的尸体吧
Presumably on his way to the morgue to identify her remains?
而之后 他发现没这个必要了
As it turned out, he was saved the trip.
# 勿忘我 #
Do not forget me
# 还记得那个少女吗 #
Remember the maid...
你是谁
Who are you?
# 那个磨坊少女 #
The maid of the mill...
你为什么这样做 你究竟是谁
Why are you doing this? Just tell me who you are!
你听出这首歌了吗 亲爱的
You recognise our song, my dear?
我在婚礼上唱过的歌
I sang it at our wedding.
艾美莉亚
Emelia?
你不可能出现在这里 你已经死了
You, you're dead, you can't be here, you died!
我美吗 托马斯
Am I not beautiful, Thomas?
是否和你娶我那天一样美
As beautiful as the day you married me?
这到底是怎么回事
What the hell is all this about?!
你觉得呢 这位英俊的朋友
What does it look like, my handsome friend?
这是一场枪杆下的婚礼
It's a shotgun wedding.
这场案子中 演绎了两次至死不渝
Till death us do part. Twice in this case.
这案子真是离奇
Extraordinary.
真是难以置信
Impossible.
这案子棒极了
Superb.
当街自杀 诈尸杀人
Suicide as street theatre, murder by corpse.
莱斯特雷德 你会宠坏我们的
Lestrade, you're spoiling us.
华生 拿上衣服和帽子
Watson, your hat and coat.
- 我们去哪里 - 去停尸房
- Where are we going? - To the morgue.
一刻也不能耽误
There's not a moment to lose,
虽然很少有人 急着去停尸房
which one can so rarely say of a morgue.
那我就在这里坐着吗
And am I just to sit here?
不用 亲爱的 我们一会就饿了
Not at all, my dear. We'll be hungry later.
福尔摩斯 我有个问题
Holmes, just one thing,
我能穿粗呢衣服 去停尸房吗
tweeds in a morgue?
形势所迫 不得不为 华生
Needs must when the devil drives, Watson.
再会 夫人
Ma'am.
- 我也是竞选的一员 - 什么竞选
- I'm part of a campaign, you know. - Oh, campaign?
- 妇女选举权 -你是支持还是反对
- Votes for women. - And are you for or against?
出去
Get out.
他们又走了吗
Oh, have they gone off again, have they?
我真不知道 他们过的是什么生活
I don't know, what a life those gentlemen lead.
是啊 这些先生们
Huh, yes. Those gentlemen!
不要在意了
Oh, never you mind.
差点忘了 这是给你的
Oh, almost forgot, that came for you.
哈德森夫人 请您转告我丈夫 我今天晚点回来
Mrs. Hudson, tell my husband I'll be home late,
我有点急事
I have some urgent business.
没出什么事吧
Is everything all right?
一个朋友找我帮忙
Oh, you know, just a, er, friend in need.
什么朋友
Oh, dear. What friend?
英国的朋友
England.
她说得也太含糊了
Well, that's not very specific.
停尸房今天谁值班
Who's on mortuary duty?
- 你知道的 - 一直是他
- You know who. - Always him.
这是哪个白痴干的
Please tell me which idiot did this!
这是为了大家的安全
It's for everyone's safety.
这女人已经死了 半边脑袋都不见了
This woman is dead, half her head is missing.
她谁都威胁不到
She's not a threat to anyone.
你去跟她丈夫说吧 他就在那边的床单下面
Tell that to her husband, he's under a sheet over there.
不管昨天晚上 莱姆豪斯发生了什么事
Whatever happened in Limehouse last night, I think
我们都可以假定 绝不是女尸干的
we can safely assume it wasn't the work of a dead woman.
更离奇的事都发生过
Stranger things have happened.
比如呢
Such as...?
就是 离奇的事
Well... Strange things.
你这话说得像个孩子
You're speaking like a child.
肯定是活人干的 他去哪了
This is clearly man's work. Where is he?
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
霍珀
Hooper.
你 回去干活
You, back to work!
用你的把戏 来震撼我们吧
So, come to astonish us with your magic tricks, I suppose?
你需要我注意什么事吗
Is there anything to which you would like to draw my attention?
完全没有 福尔摩斯先生
Nothing at all, Mr. Holmes.
您想待多久都行
You may leave any time you like.
霍珀医生 是我请福尔摩斯先生过来的
Dr. Hooper, I asked Mr. Holmes to come here.
请你配合一点
Cooperate.
这是命令
That's an order.
有"两个特征值得注意"
There are two "Features of interest",
正如你常在 华生医生的故事中所说
as you are always saying in Dr. Watson's stories.
我从没说过这话
I never say that.
你说过 很多次
You do, actually, quite a lot.
首先 这就是艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂的尸体
First of all, this is definitely Emelia Ricoletti.
她的身份已经确定
She has been categorically identified.
毋庸置疑 这就是她
Beyond a doubt, it is her.
那昨晚出现在莱姆豪斯的是谁
Then who was that in Limehouse last night?
那位也是艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
That was also Emelia Ricoletti.
不可能 她死了 她一直在这里
It can't have been. She was dead, she was here.
她丈夫临死之前几秒钟
She was positively identified
才确认过她的身份
by her own husband, seconds before he died.
他没有理由说谎 也不可能搞错
He had no reason to lie, could hardly have been mistaken.
车夫也指认了 那的确就是她
The cabbie knew her, too, there's no question it's her.
但她不可能 同时出现在两个地方
But she can't have been in two places at the same time, can she?
没错 华生
No, Watson, one place is
刚离世的人 只能在一个地方出现
strictly the limit for the recently deceased.
我知道了 福尔摩斯
Holmes!
- 她们可能是双胞胎吗 - 不可能
- Could it have been twins? - No.
为什么
Why not?
她就没有双胞胎姐妹
Because it's never twins.
艾美莉亚甚至连同胞姐妹都没有
Emelia was not a twin, nor did she have any sisters.
她有个哥哥 四年前去世了
She had one older brother who died four years ago.
有可能是没公开的孪生姐妹
Hmm, maybe it was a secret twin.
什么
A what?!
没公开的孪生姐妹
A secret twin.
你听懂了吗
Hmm? You know?
就是没人知道的双胞胎
A twin that nobody knows about.
整个案子可能都是策划好的
This whole thing could have been planned.
从怀孕就开始策划吗
Since the moment of conception.
她可真是有远见
How breathtakingly prescient of her.
- 不可能是双胞胎 华生 - 那你怎么看
- It is never twins, Watson! - Then what's your theory?
更重要的一点是 你又是什么毛病
More to the point, what's your problem?
- 你什么意思 - 你在害怕什么
- I... I don't understand... - Why were you so frightened?
目前为止 还无法合理解释 你为何突袭我的酒壶
Nothing so far has justified your assault on my decanter,
还有你为什么 要让人监禁一具女尸
and why have you allowed a dead woman to be placed under arrest?
这个特征也很值得我们注意
Ah, that would be the other feature of interest.
她手指上有血迹
A smear of blood on her finger.
留下血迹的原因可太多了
That could have happened any number of ways.
没错 还有一件事
Indeed. There's one other thing.
这块血迹 是之后留下的
It wasn't there earlier.
那边的血迹也一样
Neither was that.
是你
You!
还是你
You?
是你吗
You?!
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
吞枪自尽 子弹贯穿头颅
Gun in the mouth, a bullet through the brain...
后脑被炸得不知去向
Back of the head blown clean off.
他是怎么活下来的
How could he survive?
是"她"吧
"She", you mean.
什么
I'm sorry?
不是"他" 是"她"
Not "He", "She".
对啊 没错
Yes, yes of course.
感谢你们提供这么有趣的案子
Well, thank you all for a fascinating case.
破案之后我会发电报给你们 走吧 华生
I'll send you a telegram when I've solved it. Watson.
虽然死因很明显是枪击
The gunshot wound was obviously the cause of death,
不过肺痨的症状也很明显
but there are clear indicators of consumption.
验尸还是很有必要的
It might be worth a postmortem.
我们得尽可能 多收集一点信息
We need all the information we can get.
老爸一走 他就有火眼金睛了
Oh, isn't he observant, now that Daddy's gone!
在某些方面 我的观察力很敏锐
I AM observant in some ways,
就像福尔摩斯 在某些方面很迟钝一样
just as Holmes is quite blind in others.
是吗
Really?
没错
Yes, really.
你想在男权社会出人头地 也真是不容易啊
Amazing... what one has to do to get ahead in a man's world.
他这话是什么意思
What's he saying that for?
回去干活
Get back to work!
福尔摩斯 说说吧 你肯定有想法了
Well, Holmes? Surely you must have some theory?
还没有 这个案子深不可测 华生 深不可测
Not yet. These are deep waters, Watson, deep waters.
但我必须深入调查
And I shall have to go deeper still.
"不出几个月之后 我们再次
"It was not for several months that we were to pick up"
被牵扯到这个奇案之中
"The threads of this strange case again."
案情也变得更加出乎意料"
"And then under very unexpected circumstances."
现在已经有五起案子了 全都一模一样
Five of them now, all the same, every one of them.
别说话 我在阅读很重要的资料
Hush, please, this is a matter of supreme importance.
什么资料
What is?
黄赤交角的问题 我得搞明白才行
The obliquity of the ecliptic. I have to understand it.
那是什么东西
What is it?
我也不知道 我正在努力学呢
I don't know, I'm still trying to understand it.
我还以为你无所不知呢
I thought you understood everything.
当然不是了
Of course not, that would be
那多浪费我的大脑空间 我有专攻领域
an appalling waste of brain space. I specialise.
那你为什么学黄赤交角
And what's so important about this?
那我为何要关心 五起无聊的谋杀案
What's so important about five boring murders?
这怎么无聊了 五个男人
They're not boring. Five men dead,
在自己家中被杀 地上撒满大米
murdered in their own homes, rice on the floor
像婚礼现场一样
like at a wedding, and
墙上还用血写着"你"
the word "You" Written in blood on the wall!
就是她 就是那个新娘干的 她不知怎么就复活了
It's, it's her, it's the Bride. Somehow she's risen again.
- 我破案了 - 你怎么可能破案了
- Solved it. - You can't have solved it!
我当然破案了 答案多简单啊
Of course I've solved it, it's perfectly simple.
神秘的瑞克莱蒂夫人杀人案 凶手
The incident of the mysterious Mrs. Ricoletti, the killer from
是来自阴间的鬼魂 从此被媒体大肆渲染
beyond the grave, has been widely reported in the popular press.
刚好凶手可以用鬼魂的传说
Now people are disguising their own dull little murders as the
掩盖自己卑劣的杀人计谋
work of a ghost, to confuse
还能迷惑 愚蠢低能的伦敦警察厅
the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard.
你看 我破案了
There you are, solved.
你出门的时候 去拜访下哈德森夫人
Pay Mrs. Hudson a visit on your way out,
她喜欢有参与感
she likes to feel involved.
你确定吗
You sure?
当然 你快走吧 华生 我准备好了
Certainly. Go away. Watson! I'm ready.
带上帽子穿好鞋 我们有个重要的约会
Your hat and boots, we have an important appointment.
华生医生不是几个月之前就搬走了吗
Didn't Dr. Watson move out a few months ago?
对 他搬走了
He did, didn't he?
那我一直都是跟谁说话呢
Who have I been talking to all this time?
请允许我代表
Well, speaking on behalf
愚蠢低能的伦敦警察厅说上一句
of the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard,
那个椅子上一直都没人
that chair is definitely empty.
确实没人 不过刚刚的画面还不错
It is, isn't it? Works surprisingly well, though.
我还以为他能有所进步呢
I actually thought he was improving.
你去哪里了
Ah. Where have you been?
抱歉 先生 我今早起晚了
Sorry, sir, I'm rather behind my time this morning.
你连鸡蛋都不会煮吗
Are you incapable of boiling an egg?!
火也基本没点 到处都是灰尘
The fires are rarely lit, there is dust everywhere
而且你在给靴子清泥的时候 差点把它毁了
and you almost destroyed my boots scraping the mud off them.
要不是我妻子负责
If it wasn't my wife's business
管理佣人 我早就亲自管教你了
to deal with the staff, I would talk to you myself.
我妻子人呢
Where is my wife?
抱歉 先生 夫人出去了
Begging your pardon, sir, but the mistress has gone out.
- 一大早就出门了 - 是的 先生
- Out? At this hour of the morning? - Yes, sir.
您不知道吗 先生
Did you not know that, sir?
她去哪里了 她最近怎么总出门
Where did she go? She's always out these days.
您不也一样 先生
Not unlike yourself... sir.
你说什么
I'm sorry...?
只是我自己的观察 先生
Just observing, sir.
够了 谁让你观察了
Well, that's quite enough, nobody asked you to be observant.
抱歉 先生 我只是注意到
Sorry, sir, I just meant
你们现在很少一起在家 先生
you're hardly ever home together any more, sir.
你现在的言行近乎无礼
You are dangerously close to impertinence.
我会告诉我妻子 让她好好管教你
I shall have a word with my wife to have a word with you.
好的 先生 您什么时候能见到夫人呢
Very good, sir. And when will you be seeing her?
你听着
Now, listen...
我差点忘了 先生 这有封您的电报
Oh, I nearly forgot, sir. A telegram came for you.
你忘了
You forgot?!
- 不是 我差点忘了 - 你这一早上都干什么了
- No, I nearly forgot. - What have you been doing all morning?
读您在"斯特兰报"刊登的新故事 先生
Reading your new one in The Strand, sir.
你喜欢我的新故事吗
Did you enjoy it?
您为什么没提到我呢 先生
Why do you never mention me, sir?
下去吧
Go away.
- 你说什么 - 我说黄赤交角
- The what of the what? - The obliquity of the ecliptic.
你说"速来" 我还以为是很重要的事
"Come at once," You said. I assumed it was important.
是很重要
It is.
黄赤交角就是
It's the inclination of
地球的赤道面 与其绕太阳运行的
the earth's equator to the path of the sun
轨道平面的夹角
on the celestial plane.
你刚学的吗
You been swotting up?
- 我为什么要学那个 - 为了显得你聪明
- Why would I do that? - To sound clever.
- 我本来就很聪明 - 我明白了
- I am clever. - Oh, oh, I see.
你明白什么了
You see what?
我推测 我们是要去见一个 比你聪明的人
I deduce we're on our way to see someone cleverer than you.
闭嘴
Shut up.
抱歉 你说什么
Sorry, what?
如果你想研究人类 这里是最合适的地方
To anyone who wishes to study mankind, this is the spot.
对你来说 也很方便
Handy really, as your
毕竟你不断膨胀的屁股 已经永远粘在这里了
ever-expanding backside is permanently glued to it.
- 早上好 哥哥 -夏洛克 华生医生
- Good morning, brother mine. - Sherlock. Dr. Watson.
你看起来 很不错 先生
You look... well, sir.
是吗 我以为自己看起来很臃肿
Really? I rather thought I looked enormous.
既然您提到了 这种暴饮暴食的行为
Well, now you mention it, this level of consumption
对您健康的危害极大
is incredibly injurious to your health.
您的心脏
Your heart...
- 不必为此担忧 华生 - 没必要吗
- No need to worry on that score, Watson. - No?
他装心脏的地方 本来就是个空腔
There's only a large cavity where that organ should reside.
- 这是家族病 - 我没有指责你的意思
- It's a family trait. - Oh, I wasn't being critical.
如果你继续这样生活
If you continue like this,
先生 我估计您最多能活五年
sir, I give you five years at the most.
- 五年 - 我们以为只有三年呢 是吧 夏洛克
- Five? - We thought three, did we not, Sherlock?
我还是倾向于四年
I'm still inclined to four.
你还是这样 只会看 不懂得观察
As ever, you see but you do not observe.
注意我眼白的颜色发生了变化
Note the discolouration in the whites of my eyes,
角膜周围出现可见的脂肪圈
the visible rings of fat around the corneas.
没错 你说得有道理
Yes, you're right. I'm changing
那我改成三年四个月零十一天
my bet to three years, four months and 11 days.
敢赌吗
A bet?!
我理解你的不赞同 华生
I understand your disapproval, Watson,
但他好胜心切
but if he's feeling competitive,
完全可以自己控制死亡时间
it's perfectly within his power to die early.
这是必须要承担的风险
That's a risk you'll have to take.
你这是在拿自己的性命打赌
You're gambling with your own life?
为何不呢 这比拿别人性命打赌 有意思多了
Why not? It's so much more exciting than gambling with others'.
这块葡萄干布丁下肚 我赌你只能活三年
Three years flat, if you eat that plum pudding!
成交
Done.
前几天的庄园一案 我以为会遇见你
I expected to see you a few days ago about the Manor House case.
我想那案子 你有点力不从心吧
I thought you might be a little out of your depth there.
不会 我已经解决了
No. I solved it.
- 肯定是亚当斯 - 对 是亚当斯
- It was Adams, of course. - Yes, it was Adams.
他是因嫉妒而杀人
Murderous jealousy. He'd
他为皇家天文学会写了一篇
written a paper for the Royal Astronomical Society
关于黄赤交角的论文
on the obliquity of the ecliptic,
然后他又读到一篇 更棒的文章
and then read another that seemed to surpass it.
- 我知道 我看了 - 你看懂了吗
- I know, I read it. - Did you understand it?
我当然能看懂 那文章非常简单
Yes, of course I understood it, it was perfectly simple.
不 你懂嫉妒杀人吗
No, did you understand the murderous jealousy?
让一个聪明人
It is no easy thing for a
去读懂更聪明人的心思 实属不易啊
great mind to contemplate a still greater one.
所以你叫我来 就是为了羞辱我吗
Did you summon me here just to humiliate me?
当然
Yes.
当然不是 但这是我目前最大的乐趣了
Of course not, but it is by far the greater pleasure.
你能否解释下叫我来的原因
Then would you mind explaining exactly why you did summon...?
我们的生活正在被 一位无形的敌人威胁着
Our way of life is under threat from an invisible enemy.
这个人每天都在我们身边徘徊
One that hovers at our elbow on a daily basis.
这些敌人无处不在 悄无声息 无人能挡
These enemies are everywhere... undetected... and unstoppable.
他们是社会主义者吗
Socialists?
不是社会主义者 医生
Not socialists, Doctor, no.
- 他们是无政府主义者吗 - 不是
Anarchists? No.
他们是法国人吗 还是妇女参政者
The French? The suffragists?
还有你没有关心到的 大规模人群吗
Is there any large body of people you're not concerned about?
华生医生永远心怀警惕 你详细说明一下
Dr. Watson is endlessly vigilant. Elaborate...
不 你去调查吧
No. Investigate.
这只是我的推测 我需要你去证实它
This is a conjecture of mine, I need you to confirm it.
我把这个案子交给你
I'm sending you a case.
- 他们是苏格兰人吧 - 什么苏格兰人
- The Scots? - The Scots?!
你知道最近有个理论是关于
Are you aware of recent theories concerning what is
妄想症的吗
known as paranoia?
这话听着像是塞尔维亚人
Oh, sounds Serbian.
有个叫卡迈克尔的女人 会去找你
A woman will call on you, Lady Carmichael.
我要你接下她的案子
I want you to take her case.
你如果不告诉我们 这些敌人是谁
But these enemies, how are we to defeat them
我们要如何打败他们
if you won't tell us about them?
我们无法打败他们 我们永远也无法战胜他们
We don't defeat them. We most certainly lose to them.
为什么
Why?
因为他们是对的 而我们是错的
Because they are right. And we are wrong.
卡迈克尔女士那里 是什么案子
Lady Carmichael's case, what is it?
放心吧 是你会感兴趣的案子
Rest assured, it has features of interest.
- 我从未这么说过 - 你真的说过
I never really say that. You really do.
我估计你已经解决了吧
And you've solved it already, I assume?
只是想通了而已 我要你帮我跑个腿
Only in my head. I need you for the, er, legwork.
为何不告诉我们 你的推理呢
Why not just tell us your solution?
那还有什么意思呢
And where would be the sport in that?
你愿意接手这个案子吗 夏洛克
Will you do it, Sherlock?
我保证这会是个极好的消遣
I can promise you a superior distraction.
我就一个条件 你再吃个葡萄干布丁吧
On one condition. Have another plum pudding.
我正准备吃呢
There's one on the way.
你只能活两年十一个月零四天了
Two years, 11 months and four days.
开始变得好玩咯 滴答 滴答
Ha, it's getting exciting now! Ticktock, ticktock, ticktock.
谢了 威尔德
Thank you, Wilder.
有一位梅拉斯先生要见你 福尔摩斯先生
Also, a Mr. Melas to see you, Mr. Holmes.
等我五分钟 我还有场赌局要赢呢
Ah. Give me five minutes, I have a wager to win.
你还是等我十五分钟吧
Better make that 15.
滴答
Ticktock.
福尔摩斯先生 我是来请你出主意的
Mr. Holmes, I have come here for advice.
- 那倒不难 - 还有您的帮助
- That is easily got. - And help.
那就未必容易了
Not always so easy.
福尔摩斯先生 我遇到了一些 不寻常的事情
Something has happened, Mr. Holmes, something... unusual
骇人听闻的事情
and... terrifying.
那你真是太幸运了
Then you are in luck.
幸运吗
Luck?!
那是我的专长 这个案子有点意思
Those are my specialisms. Hmm, this is really very promising.
福尔摩斯
Holmes...
请告诉我们 您在苦恼些什么
Please... do tell us what has so distressed you.
我思前想后很久 不知该怎么办
I... I thought long and hard as to what to do,
后来突然想起 我丈夫与您的哥哥相识
but then it occurred to me that my husband was
所以也许通过他...
an acquaintance of your brother and that perhaps through him...
其实我也不太确定
The fact is, I'm not sure
这事是否在您的管辖范围内 福尔摩斯先生
this comes within your purview, Mr. Holmes.
是吗
No?
上帝啊 也许我该找个驱魔师
Lord help me, I think it may be a matter for a priest.
你早晨受到什么惊吓了 亲爱的
And what does your morning threaten, my dear?
刺绣做地停不下来吗
A vigorous round of embroidering?
还是跟女帽商们见面太频繁了
An exhausting appointment at the milliners?
你就喜欢取笑我 尤斯塔斯
I hope you are teasing, Eustace.
怎么了
What is it?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?
丹尼尔 苏菲 你们去外面玩会
Daniel, Sophie, go out and play.
但是 妈妈
But, Mama...
听话 快去吧
Look, do as I tell you, quickly now.
尤斯塔斯 这是什么东西
Well, Eustace, what does this mean?
死亡
Death.
什么
What?
这意味着死亡
It means death.
没什么 没什么
Er, nothing, it's, er, it's nothing.
我弄错了
I was... mistaken.
亲爱的 你脸色好苍白
My dear, you've gone quite pale.
我没事
It's nothing!
- 尤斯塔斯 - 信封你还留着吗
- Eustace... - 'Did you keep the envelope?'
我丈夫销毁了 但上面什么都没有
My husband destroyed it, but it was blank.
没有姓名 没有地址
No name or address of any kind.
尤斯塔斯先生有在美国待过吗
Tell me, has Sir Eustace spent time in America?
- 没有 - 你们结婚之前 也没有吗
- No. - Not even before your marriage?
- 据我所知没有 - 好吧
- Well, not to my knowledge. - Hmm.
请您接着讲 这个令人着迷的故事吧
Pray, continue with your fascinating narrative.
那件事 发生在上周一的清晨
Well, that incident took place last Monday morning.
两天后 也就是周三
It was two days later on
我丈夫第一次看见了她
the Wednesday that my husband first saw her.
看见了谁
Who?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?
她来找我了 路易莎
She's come for me, Louisa!
天啊 帮帮我 我的罪孽找到我了
Oh, God, help me, my sins have found me out!
谁来找你了 尤斯塔斯 你吓到我了
Who's come for you? Eustace, you're frightening me.
看啊 看啊
Well, look, look!
你没看见她吗
Don't you see her?
我什么也没看见
No, I see no-one.
她走了
Gone.
这又是一个 你瞒着我的秘密吗
You keep so many secrets from me, is this another?
你看见了谁
Who have you seen?
是她
It was her!
那个鬼新娘
It was the Bride!
但你什么也没看见吗
And you saw nothing?
是的
Nothing.
- 你丈夫有描述过... - 没有 直到今天早晨
- Did your husband describe...? - Nothing, until this morning.
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
尤斯塔斯 是你吗
Eustace?
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
该死的
Blast!
尤斯塔斯
Eustace?!
你去哪里了 是我啊
Where are you? It's me!
# 勿忘我 #
Do not forget me
# 还记得那少女吗 #
Remember the maid
# 那个磨坊少女 #
The maid of the mill...
你是谁
Who are you?
我命令你 报上名来
I demand you speak, who are you?!
尤斯塔斯 说句话啊 天啊
Eustace, speak to me. In the name of God!
她是...
She's...
她是艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
She is Emelia Ricoletti.
不 不可能是你
No, not you.
不要
No...
求你了
Please!
今晚 尤斯塔斯·卡迈克尔 你必死无疑
This night, Eustace Carmichael, you will die!
- 福尔摩斯 - 别出声 华生
- Holmes? - Hush, Watson.
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂 那个新娘
But Emelia Ricoletti, the Bride.
- 你知道她的名字吗 - 请原谅华生
- Well, you know the name? - You must forgive Watson,
他就热衷于说一些
he has an enthusiasm for
显而易见的事实 他就喜欢这样
stating the obvious, which borders on mania.
请问 您丈夫今早还好吗
May I ask, how is your husband this morning?
他拒绝谈论此事
He refuses to speak about the matter.
显然 我已催促 让他离开家
Obviously, I have urged him to leave the house.
不行 他必须得待在家里
No, no, he must stay exactly where he is.
您不觉得 他正处于危险之中吗
Well, you don't think he's in danger?
当然 的确是有人
Oh, no, somebody definitely
想害他性命 但对我们来说是件好事
wants to kill him, but that's good for us.
要设陷阱 还需先有诱饵
You can't set a trap without bait.
我丈夫可不是诱饵 福尔摩斯先生
My husband is not bait, Mr. Holmes.
如果我们确保万无一失 就没有关系
No, but he could be if we play our cards right.
听着 你现在立刻回家
Now, listen, you must go home immediately.
华生医生和我会乘坐下一班火车过去
Dr. Watson and I will follow on the next train.
一刻也不能耽搁 尤斯塔斯爵士今夜会死
There's not a moment to lose, Sir Eustace is to die tonight.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我们也许能避免此事
And we should... probably avoid that.
- 是一定 - 一定会避免此事
- Definitely. - Definitely avoid that.
当然 我弟弟接下了这件案子
Little brother has taken the case, of course.
那就拜托你 帮我多留心此事了
I now rely on you to keep an eye on things,
但绝不能让他怀疑 你在为我办事
but he must never suspect you are working for me.
听清楚了吗 华生
Are you clear on that, Watson?
请相信我 福尔摩斯先生
You can rely on me, Mr. Holmes.
- 你说会不会 - 不会 你也不该有这种想法
You don't suppose... - I don't and neither should you.
你又不知道我打算说什么
You don't know what I was going to say.
你是想说 可能有什么超自然的力量
You were about to suggest there may be some supernatural agency
牵扯其中 而我正准备当面嘲笑你
involved in this matter. And I was about to laugh in your face.
但那个新娘 艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂再次出现了
But the Bride, Holmes, Emelia Ricoletti again.
一名死去的女子又重现人间
A dead woman walking the earth.
- 你真让我惊讶啊 华生 - 是吗
- You amaze me, Watson. - I do?
你什么时候开始 居然这么有想象力了
Since when have you had any kind of imagination?
估计自从我让读者们相信
Perhaps since I convinced the reading public that
道德败坏的瘾君子
an unprincipled drug addict
也能是风度翩翩的英雄人物吧
was some kind of gentleman hero.
是啊 提到这事 你还真是了不起啊
Yes, now you come to mention it, that was quite impressive.
你放心 这个世界上没有鬼
You may, however, rest assured there are no ghosts in this world.
鬼怪只来自我们心中
Save those we make for ourselves.
抱歉 你这话是什么意思
Sorry, what did you say?
我们想象出的鬼 这是什么意思
Ghosts we make for ourselves, what do you mean?
我有梦游症
Somnambulism.
您说什么
I beg your pardon?
我会梦游 就这样 不是什么大事
I sleepwalk, that's all. It's a common enough condition.
您不就是医生吗
I thought you were a doctor!
整件事就是一场恶梦
The whole thing was a... bad dream.
包括您收到的 信封里的东西吗
Including the contents of the envelope you received?
那只是个奇怪的玩笑
Well, that's a grotesque joke.
您妻子感觉并非如此啊 先生
Well, that's not the impression you gave your wife, sir.
- 她有臆想病 很容易幻想 - 并非如此
- She's an hysteric, prone to fancies. - No.
-很抱歉 您说什么 - 我说不对 她并没有臆想病
- I'm sorry, what did you say? - I said no, she's not an hysteric.
她是个有着罕见洞察力的聪明女人
She's a highly intelligent woman of rare perception.
我的妻子从橙核里看出了恐惧
My wife sees terror in an orange pip.
你的妻子能在别人认为毫无价值的地方
Your wife can see worlds where no-one else can see
看出很多东西
anything of value whatsoever.
真的吗
Can she really?
那您是如何"推理"出来的呢 福尔摩斯先生
And how do you "Deduce" That, Mr. Holmes?
她嫁给了你
She married you.
我想她一定有合理的理由
I assume she was capable of finding a reason.
今晚我会竭尽全力护你周全 但首先
I'll do my best to save your life tonight, but first it would
如果您能解释与瑞克莱蒂一案的关系
help if you would explain your connection.
我想定会大有帮助
to the Ricoletti case.
瑞克莱蒂
Ricoletti?
是的 请详情说来
Yes. In detail, please.
我从未听说过她
I've never heard of her.
有意思 我并没有提到 她是个女人
Interesting. I didn't mention she was a woman.
我们先告辞了 希望明早还能再见到你
We'll show ourselves out. I hope to see you again in the morning.
我们不会再见面了
You will not.
那可真是不幸 那我就得来破你的谋杀案了 再会
Then sadly I shall be solving your murder. Good day.
你尽力了
Well, you tried.
请转交给卡迈克尔夫人 谢谢
Will you see that Lady Carmichael receives this. Thank you.
- 午安 - 没问题 先生
- Good afternoon. - Certainly, sir.
那是什么
What was that?
卡迈克尔夫人今晚
Lady Carmichael will sleep alone tonight,
会假装头痛难忍 而独自就寝
upon the pretence of a violent headache.
所有的门窗都会上锁
All the doors and windows of the house will be locked.
你觉得那幽灵 那鬼新娘
Ha! You think the spectre, er, Bride,
会再次试图将尤斯塔斯爵士 引到外面去吗
will attempt to lure Sir Eustace outside again?
当然 不然她为何口出狂言
Certainly. Why else the portentous threat?
- "今晚你必死无疑" - 他不会跟出去的吧
- "This night you will die!" - Well, he won't follow her, surely?
他会怎么做 还真的很难说
Hmm, it's difficult to say quite what he'll do.
- 愧疚在吞噬他的灵魂 - 愧疚 什么愧疚
- Guilt is eating away at his soul. - Guilt? About what?
他的过去 那些橙核是个提醒
Something in his past. The orange pips were a reminder.
- 不是玩笑吗 - 完全不是
- Not a joke? - Not at all.
有一个传统是用橙核
Orange pips are a traditional
来预警复仇偿命的 这个起源于美国
warning of avenging death, originating in America.
尤斯塔斯爵士对此再了解不过了
Sir Eustace knows this only too well,
他很清楚自己 为何要受惩罚
just as he knows why he is to be punished.
是和艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂有关吗
Something to do with Emelia Ricoletti?
我想是的 我们都有过去 华生 而鬼魂
I presume. We all have a past, Watson. Ghosts.
他们如同阴霾 正是因为有了阴霾 才会出现阳光
They are the shadows that define our every sunny day.
尤斯塔斯爵士知道自己是逃不过了
Sir Eustace knows he's a marked man.
他恐惧的不仅仅是死亡
There's something more than murder he fears.
他深信死去的瑞克莱蒂太太复活的尸体
He believes he is to be dragged to hell by the risen corpse
会将他拖入万丈深渊
of the late Mrs. Ricoletti.
那也太荒谬了吧
That's a lot of nonsense, isn't it?
老天 当然荒谬了 你的左轮手枪带了吗
God, yes. Did you bring your revolver?
用手枪对付幽灵有用吗
What good would that be against a ghost?
- 那当然 你带了吗 - 嗯 带了
- Exactly. Did you bring it? - Yeah, of course.
那就来吧 华生 来吧 游戏开始了
Then come, Watson, come. The game is afoot.
- 蹲下来 华生 老天啊 - 抱歉 我抽筋了
- Get down, Watson, for heaven's sake! - Sorry. Cramp.
- 灯还亮着吗 - 是的
- Is the lamp still burning? - Yes.
尤斯塔斯爵士的灯灭了
There goes Sir Eustace.
卡迈克尔夫人的灯也灭了
And Lady Carmichael.
整栋房子都入睡了
The house sleeps.
天啊 这是我这一生之中 最漫长的一夜了
Hmm, good God, this is the longest night of my life.
耐心点 华生
Have patience, Watson.
就到午夜而已
Only midnight.
我们很少像现在这样坐在一起
You know, it's rare for us to sit together like this.
我觉得也是 但现在谋杀案迫在眉睫
I should hope so. It's murder on the knees.
两个老朋友说说话 聊聊天
Two old friends just talking. Chewing the fat.
男人和男人之间的对话
Man-to-man.
那个不同寻常的女人
So, a remarkable woman.
- 谁 - 卡迈克尔夫人
- Who? - Lady Carmichael.
女性方面可是你的专长 华生
The fair sex is your department, Watson.
我接受你的评价
I'll take your word for it.
你挺喜欢她的 "那个女人有罕见的洞察力"
Well, you liked her. "A woman of rare perception."
和令人赞叹的高足弓
And admirably high arches.
她一踏进房间我就注意到了
I noticed them as soon as she stepped into the room.
- 他根本配不上她 - 你这么认为吗
- Huh, she's far too good for him. - You think so?
不 是你这么认为 我能看出来
No. You think so. I could tell.
相反 我对此事一点都不在意
On the contrary, I have no view on the matter.
你就是在意
Yes, you have.
- 婚姻不是我会想的东西 - 为什么
- Marriage is not a subject upon which I dwell. - Oh, why not?
你今晚是怎么了
What's the matter with you this evening?
你戴着的那个怀表 里面有一张照片
That watch that you're wearing, there's a photograph inside it.
我有一次瞥见了 我想那是艾琳·艾德勒的照片
I glimpsed it once. I believe it is of Irene Adler.
你才不是瞥见的 你是等我睡着之后
You didn't glimpse it, you waited till I'd fallen asleep
- 自己偷看的 - 是的
- and looked at it. - Yes, I did.
- 你真以为我没注意到吗 - 艾琳·艾德勒
- You seriously thought I wouldn't notice? - Irene Adler.
一个强大的对手 一次难忘的冒险经历
Formidable opponent, a remarkable adventure.
- 那照片很好看 - 你说这些干什么
- A very nice photograph. - Why are you talking like this?
你为何立志要孤身一人
Why are you so determined to be alone?
你还好吧 华生
Are you quite well, Watson?
这是个奇怪的问题吗
Is it such a curious question?
对一个维也纳的精神病医生来说 不是
From a Viennese alienist, no.
但对一个退役军医来说 当然是
From a retired Army surgeon, most certainly.
福尔摩斯 我绝非是你的对手
Holmes, against absolutely no opposition whatsoever,
- 我是你最亲近的朋友 - 我承认
- I am your closest friend. - I concede it.
我现在只是尝试跟你进行一段
I am currently attempting to have
非常正常的对话而已
a perfectly normal conversation with you.
- 求你别了 - 你为什么非得一个人呢
- Please don't. - Why do you need to be alone?
如果你说的是 关于情感纠葛的事 华生
If you are referring to romantic entanglement, Watson,
恐怕你说的就是这个 就像我以前经常解释的那样
which I rather fear you are, as I have often explained before,
我讨厌所有的情感
all emotion is abhorrent to me.
情感是精密仪器上的沙粒
It is the grit in a sensitive instrument.
- 镜头上的裂缝 - 镜头上的裂缝 是的
- The crack in the lens. - The crack in the lens. Yes.
明白了吧 我之前告诉过你
Well, there you are, you see, I've said it all before.
不 这些都是我写的
No, I wrote all that.
你在引用"斯特兰德杂志"里自己的话
You're quoting yourself from The Strand Magazine.
- 正是 - 那是我写的 不是你说的
- Well, exactly. - Those are my words, not yours!
那是我向公众呈现的 你的样子
That is the version of you that I present to the public.
没有情感的头脑 就像一台计算机
The brain without a heart. The calculating machine.
那些都是我写的 福尔摩斯 读者也欣然接受了
I write all of that, Holmes, and the readers lap it up.
但我并不相信这个事实
But I do not believe it.
我想给你的编辑写信
Well, I've a good mind to write to your editor.
你是一个活生生的人
You are a living, breathing man.
- 你有自己的生活 也有过去 - 有什么
- You've lived a life, you have a past. - A what?!
- 你肯定有过... - 有过什么
- Well, you must have had... - Had what?
- 你知道的 - 不知道
- You know. - No.
经历
Experiences.
把你的左轮手枪给我 我突然想用一下
Pass me your revolver, I have a sudden need to use it.
可恶 福尔摩斯 你是血肉之躯
Damn it, Holmes, you are flesh and blood,
你有感觉 你有...
you have feelings, you have...
你肯定会有 冲动
You must have... impulses.
我的天啊 我从来没有像这样
Dear Lord, I have never been
想马上被杀人厉鬼袭击的感觉
so impatient to be attacked by a murderous ghost.
作为你的朋友 作为一个担心你的人
As your friend, as someone who worries about you...
是什么事情 造就了你性格
What made you like this?
华生
Oh, Watson...
无事造就了我
Nothing made me.
我造就了自己
I made me.
红胡子
Redbeard?
我的天啊
Good God!
我们该怎么办
What are we to do?
我们去跟她聊会天吧
Why don't we have a chat?
我想你是瑞克莱蒂夫人吧
Mrs. Ricoletti, I believe!
每年的今晚 真是宜人 对吧
A pleasant night for the time of year, is it not?
这不可能是真的 福尔摩斯 这不可能
It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot!
对 不可能
No, it can't.
- 门锁上了吗 - 按要求锁着呢
- Is it locked? - As per instruction.
那是打破窗户的声音吗
That was a window breaking, wasn't it?
我们只用担心 一扇打破的窗户就行了
There's only one broken window we need concern ourselves with.
- 待在这里 华生 - 什么 我不要
- Stay here, Watson. - What? No.
房子里所有的窗户 和门都上了锁
All the doors and windows to the house are locked.
这是他们唯一的出口 我需要你在这守着
This is their only way out, I need you here!
但那个声音那么近
But the sound was so close.
肯定是从房子这边传来的
It had to be from this side of the house.
待在这里
Stay here!
不
No!
你保证会护他安全 你保证过的
You promised to keep him safe. You promised!
你
You...
你是人 我知道
You're human, I know that.
你肯定是人
You must be.
我们站在黑暗中也没用
Little use us standing here in the dark.
毕竟 这是十九世纪了
After all, this is the 19th century.
勿忘我
Do not forget me!
华生
Watson!
她在那里 她就在那里
She's there! She's down there!
别告诉我 你擅离职守了
Don't tell me you abandoned your post!
什么 福尔摩斯 她就在那里 我看见她了
What? Holmes, she's there, I saw her!
没人 这都得感谢你
Empty, thanks to you!
我们的目标跑了
Our bird is flown!
不 福尔摩斯 不是你想的那样
No! No, Holmes, it wasn't what you think.
我看见她了 那个鬼魂
I saw her! The ghost!
世界上 没有 鬼魂
There are no ghosts!
那发生什么事了 尤斯塔斯先生在哪里
What happened? Where is Sir Eustace?
他死了
Dead.
你不需要责怪自己
You really mustn't blame yourself, you know.
- 你说得对 - 很高兴你终于明事理了
- No, you're quite right. - I'm glad you're seeing sense.
华生也该受罚
Watson is equally culpable.
我们已经设法 搞砸了整个案子
Between us, we've managed to botch this whole case.
我承诺过要保护那个男人
I gave an undertaking to protect that man,
但他现在躺在那里 胸口上还插着把匕首
now he's lying there with a dagger in his breast.
事实上 你只是承诺过 要调查他的谋杀案
In fact, you gave an undertaking to investigate his murder.
因为我非常相信 他一定不会死
In the confident expectation I would not have to!
你发现什么了吗 医生
Anything you can tell us, Doctor?
捅他的人力气可不小
Well, he's been stabbed with considerable force.
- 凶手是个男人吗 - 有可能
- It's a man, then? - Possibly.
刀刃非常锋利 所以也有可能是个女人吧
A very keen blade, so it could conceivably have been a woman?
理论上来说 是的 但我们知道是谁 我看见她了
In theory, yes, but we know who it was, I saw her.
- 华生 - 我亲眼看见那个鬼魂了
- Watson! - I saw the ghost, with my own eyes!
你看到的都是假象
You saw nothing!
是他们想要你 看见那个鬼魂
You saw what you were supposed to see!
你自己也说过 我没有想象力
You said yourself, I have no imagination.
那你就动脑啊 尽管没什么用
Then use your brain, such as it is,
至少能排除掉不可能的因素
to eliminate the impossible,
在这桩案件中 鬼魂就是不可能因素
which in this case is the ghost,
然后再观察其它的线索
and observe what remains,
这桩案子的谜底
which in this case is a solution
已经明显到 连莱斯特雷德都能看出来了
so blindingly obvious even Lestrade could work it out!
谢谢夸奖
Thank you!
别去想另一个世界的幽灵了
Forget spectres from the other world!
只有一个嫌疑人有动机 也有机会
There is only one suspect with motive and opportunity.
- 他们可能又留了字条 - 他们确实留了字条
- They might as well have left a note. - They did leave a note.
还有另一扇破窗户的问题
And then there's the matter of the other broken window.
- 什么另一扇破窗户 - 正是 没有另一扇
- What other broken window? - Precisely! There isn't one.
唯一被打破的窗户
The only broken window is
就是我和华生进来的那扇
the one that Watson and I entered through,
但在那之前 我们清晰地听到了声音
yet, prior to that, we distinctly heard the sound of...
- 你刚说了什么 - 什么
- What did you just say? - Sorry?
关于字条的事 你刚说了什么
About a note, what did you just say?
- 我说凶手确实留了张字条 - 不 他们没留
- I said the murderer DID leave a note. - No, they didn't.
匕首上绑了一张字条 你看定看见了
There's a message tied to the dagger. You must have seen it!
- 根本没有字条 - 有的
- There's no message. - Yes!
我发现尸体的时候 根本没有字条
There was no message when I found the body.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
上面写了什么
What is it?
你想吗
Do you?
想什么
Do I what?
你怎么拿到这个的
H... how did you get that?
我把它留在犯罪现场了
I left it at the crime scene.
"犯罪现场" 你从哪里
"Crime scene"? Where do
学来的这些 奇怪的表达方式
you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你想他吗
Do you miss him?
莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty is dead.
但是呢
And yet...?
没有人找到他的尸体
His body was never recovered.
你推下的可是一位数学教授
To be expected when one
这种结果也在预料之中
pushes a maths professor over a waterfall.
纯粹的理性被情节剧推翻了
Pure reason toppled by sheer melodrama.
一句话概括你的人生
Your life in a nutshell.
你又从哪里学来 这些奇怪的表达方式
Where do you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你又胖了吗
Have you put on weight?
你昨天刚见过我 你觉得可能吗
You saw me only yesterday. Does that seem possible?
- 不可能 - 但我确实胖了
- No. - Yet here I am, increased.
整个英格兰
What does that tell the
最著名的犯罪调查人员 从中看出什么了
foremost criminal investigator in England?
整个英格兰
In England?
你陷得很深 夏洛克 比你想象中还要深
You're in deep, Sherlock, deeper than you ever intended to be.
- 你列了清单吗 - 什么清单
- Have you made a list? - Of what?
所有的事情 我们会需要一张清单
Everything. We will need a list.
好孩子
Good boy.
不 我还没有完成清单
No, I haven't finished yet.
莫里亚蒂恕不同意
Moriarty may beg to differ.
他想要我分心 要我脱离正轨
He's trying to distract me. To derail me.
是的
Yes.
他是镜头上的裂缝 软膏里的苍蝇
He's the crack in the lens, the fly in the ointment,
数据中的病毒
the virus in the data.
我必须了结这一切
I have to finish this.
如果莫里亚蒂真的 从赖兴巴赫瀑布下 起死回生了
If Moriarty has risen from the Reichenbach cauldron,
他会来找你的
he will seek you out.
那我就等着他了
I'll be waiting.
是啊
Yes.
恐怕你会等到他的
I'm very much afraid you will.
他已经那个样子两天了
Two days he's been like that.
- 他吃东西了吗 - 一口都没吃
- Has he eaten? - No, not a morsel.
媒体的大好机会来了
Press are having a ruddy field day.
到现在还有记者在外面等着
There's still reporters outside.
他们一直都在那里 我没法摆脱他们
Oh, they've been there all the time, I can't get rid of them.
我一直都在忙着给他们泡茶呢
I've been rushed off my feet making tea.
你为什么要给他们泡茶
Why do you make them tea?
我不知道 我就是这样做了
I dunno, I just sort of do.
他说了 "只有一个嫌疑人" 然后就离开了
He said, "There's only one suspect," And then he just walks away
现在他又不做推理
and now he won't explain.
真奇怪 他向来很喜欢推理的
Which is strange, because he likes that bit.
他还说这案子简单到 我都能解决了
Said it was so simple I could solve it.
他肯定只是夸张而已
I'm sure he was exaggerating.
你觉得他这是在干什么呢
What's he doing, do you think?
- 他说他在等 - 等什么
- He says he's waiting. - For what?
等恶魔 我不觉得这有什么奇怪
The devil. I wouldn't be surprised.
什么样的人都来过这里
We get all sorts here.
- 有消息就给我发电报 - 好
- Well, wire me if there's any change. - Yeah.
我要说的话 你都已经知道了吧
Everything I have to say has already crossed your mind.
那我的答案 你也都知道了吧
Then possibly my answer has crossed yours.
像子弹般穿过
Like a bullet.
手拿睡袍里
It's a dangerous habit,
上了膛的手枪 可是个危险的习惯
to finger loaded firearms in the pocket of one's dressing gown.
还是说你很高兴看到我
Or are you just pleased to see me?
你一定不会介意 我做些预防措施
You'll forgive me for taking precautions.
如果你没做防御措施 我才介意呢
I'd be offended if you didn't.
很显然 我也礼尚往来了
Obviously, I've returned the courtesy.
我喜欢你的房间 闻起来非常得
I like your rooms. They smell so...
有男子气概
manly.
你肯定在此之前就来过这里了
I'm sure you acquainted yourself with them before now.
你总是不在家
Well, you are always away,
总在为"斯特兰德杂志"出去冒险
on your little adventures for The Strand.
告诉我 插画师也跟你一起出去旅行吗
Tell me, does the illustrator travel with you?
你推理的时候 还要摆姿势吗
Do you have to pose... during your deductions?
我不在的时候 你来过我公寓六次了
I'm aware of all six occasions you have visited these apartments
- 我都注意到了 - 我知道
- during my absence. - I know you are.
顺便说一句 你的床真是很舒服啊
By the way, you have a surprisingly comfortable bed.
你知道灰尘大部分 是人体皮屑组成的吗
Did you know that dust is largely composed of human skin?
我知道
Yes.
不过尝起来不太一样 人的皮肤还是更新鲜些
Doesn't taste the same, though, you want your skin fresh.
- 这个有点太脆了 - 你不坐下吗
- Just a little crispy. - Won't you sit down?
人就是这样 你知道吧
That's all people really are, you know,
都是随风飘散的灰尘
dust waiting to be distributed.
而且飘得到处都是
And it gets everywhere. Ugh.
存在于每一口呼吸里 在每一缕阳光里起舞的
In every breath you take, dancing in every sunbeam,
都是精疲力竭的人啊
all the used-up people.
真有意思 你还是坐下...
Fascinating, I'm sure. Won't you sit...
人啊 无法保持一尘不染
People, people, people! Can't keep anything shiny.
你介意我开枪吗
Do you mind if I fire this?
就清理一下灰尘而已
Just to clean it out.
就是这样 还是别玩了
Exactly, let's stop playing.
我们不需要用玩具来杀掉对方
We don't need toys to kill each other.
- 那样就不亲密了 - 坐下
- Where's the intimacy in that? - Sit down.
- 为什么 你想知道什么 - 是你选择过来的
- Why? What do you want? - You chose to come here.
不对 你知道这个答案是错误的
Not true, you know that's not true.
你想知道什么 夏洛克
What do you want, Sherlock?
真相
The truth.
那个啊 真相很无聊的
That. Truth's boring!
你没想到我会
You didn't expect me to
出现在犯罪现场 对吧
turn up at the scene of the crime, did you?
可怜的尤斯塔斯先生 他罪有应得
Poor old Sir Eustace. He got what was coming to him.
但不可能是你杀了他
But you couldn't have killed him.
那又怎么样 这很重要吗 真是够了
Oh, so what? Does it matter? Stop it. Stop this.
你根本不在乎尤斯塔斯先生
You don't care about Sir Eustace,
或是那个新娘 或是其他东西
or the Bride, or any of it.
这整个案件中只有一件事
There's only one thing in
你觉得有意思
this whole business that you find interesting.
我知道你在干什么
I know what you're doing.
新娘把枪放进了嘴里
The Bride put a gun in
把自己后脑勺都打开花了
her mouth and shot the back of her head off
但她却又起死回生了
and then she came back.
不可能的事 但她做到了
Impossible. But she did it.
你想知道她是怎么做到的
And you need to know how.
这究竟是怎么回事
How?
是不是
Don't you?
因为这个谜团 你的世界都要分崩离析了
It's tearing your world apart, not knowing.
你是想阻止我 让我分心 让我脱离正轨
You're trying to stop me... To distract me, derail me.
因为这让你想起了另一个案子吧
Because doesn't this remind you of another case?
这一切以前都发生过吧
Hasn't this all happened before?
天下原无新鲜事 以前发生过什么事情
There's nothing new under the sun. What was it?
是什么事情 是什么案子
What was it? What was that case? Huh?
你记得吗
Do you remember?
就在我嘴边了 我要说出来了
It's on the tip of my tongue. It's on the tip of my tongue.
我马上就要说出来了
It's on the tip of my tongue.
就在
It's on the tip...
我舌头上了
of my tongue.
为了哈德森夫人的墙纸着想 我得提醒你
For the sake of Mrs. Hudson's wallpaper, I must remind you
你的手指乱动一下 你就会死
that one false move with your finger and you will be dead.
你说什么
I'm sorry?
死亡 是新的性感体验
Dead... is the new sexy.
这一枪把我彻底打醒了
Well, I'll tell you what, that rather blows the cobwebs away.
- 你怎么可能还活着 - 我看起来怎么样
- How can you be alive? - How do I look?
你跟我说实话 这很显眼是吧
You can be honest, is it noticeable?
你打穿了自己的大脑 怎么可能还活着
You blew your own brains out, how could you survive?
我梳个背头 应该能挡住
Or maybe I could backcomb.
我亲眼看到你死了
I saw you die.
你为什么还没死
Why aren't you dead?
因为不是瀑布害死了你 夏洛克
Because it's not the fall that kills you, Sherlock.
你比所有人都清楚 不是瀑布
Of all people, you should know that, it's not the fall,
瀑布不会害死你
it's never the fall.
你是在降落了
It's the landing!
我们着陆了 先生 我们已经着陆了
We've landed, sir. We've landed.
别 别现在叫醒我
No, no, not now, not now!
别现在醒来啊
Not now, not now.
我相信您 度过了个愉快的航程 先生
I trust you had a pleasant flight, sir?
这流放比我们想得还要短 我的弟弟
Well, a somewhat shorter exile than we'd imagined, brother mine,
不过你作为重度强迫症患者 大概也足够长了
but probably adequate, given your levels of OCD.
- 我得回去 - 什么
- I have to go back! - What?
我 我就快明白了 我马上就知道了
I was... I was nearly there, I nearly had it!
你到底在说什么东西
What on earth are you talking about?
回哪里去 你没飞多远啊
Go back where? You didn't get very far.
瑞克莱蒂和他可恶的妻子 你们懂了吗
Ricoletti and his abominable wife! Don't you understand?!
不 我们当然不懂 你在说胡话呢 夏洛克
No, of course we don't, you're not making any sense, Sherlock.
那是一个一百年前的名案
It was a case, a famous one from 100 years ago.
存在我的硬盘里
Lodged in my hard drive,
她本应该死了 却又死而复生
she seemed to be dead, but then she came back.
什么 像莫里亚蒂一样吗
What, like Moriarty?
朝着头开了一枪 跟莫里亚蒂一模一样
Shot herself in the head, exactly like Moriarty.
但是你才刚刚知道
But you've only just been told.
我们也是刚刚才知道
We've only just found out,
他出现在了全国所有的电视屏幕上
he's on every TV screen in the country.
所以呢 迈克罗夫特的电话 都已经打来五分钟了
Yes? So? It's been five minutes since Mycroft called.
你们有什么进展 你们做了什么事情
What progress have you made? What have you been doing?
更重要的是 你又做了什么事情
More to the point, what have YOU been doing?
我当然一直在思维殿堂里
I've been in my Mind Palace, of course.
当然了
Of course.
做一个实验 如果我在1895年的现场
Running an experiment. How would I have solved the crime,
- 我会怎么破这个案 - 夏洛克
- if I'd been there in 1895? - Oh, Sherlock.
我掌握了所有的细节
I had all the details perfect.
我就在现场 万事俱备 我正沉浸其中
I was there, all of it, everything. I was immersed.
是啊 正是如此
Of course you were.
你一直在读约翰的博客 你们相遇的故事
You've been reading John's blog. The story of how you met.
有些时候通过他的视角 审视自己很有帮助
It helps me if I see myself through his eyes sometimes.
我比他聪明多了
I'm so much cleverer.
你觉得有谁 会相信你的话吗
Do you really think anyone is believing you?
不 他能做到 我见过的
No, he can do this, I've seen it.
思维殿堂 好像全世界都在他的脑中
The Mind Palace, it's like a whole world in his head.
是啊 我需要回到那里
Yes, and I need to get back there.
思维殿堂是一种记忆技巧 我知道它能做什么事情
The Mind Palace is a memory technique, I know what it can do
我也知道它绝不能做什么事情
and I know what it most certainly cannot.
也许有一两件事 是我知道 而你却不知道的
Maybe there are one or two things that I know that you don't.
确实有 你列清单了吗
Oh, there are. Did you make a list?
你胖了
You've put on weight.
你穿的西装背心 明显要比夹克新
That waistcoat is clearly newer than the jacket.
够了 你列清单了吗
Stop this! Just stop it! Did you make a list?!
什么清单
Of what?
夏洛克 你摄入的所有东西
Everything, Sherlock. Everything you've taken.
不 他没有嗑药 嗑药后
No, it's not that, he goes
他会进入一种恍惚状态 我见过他那样
into a sort of trance. I've seen him do it.
从那一天起 我和我弟弟 就做了一个约定
We have an agreement, my brother and I, ever since that day.
不管我在哪里找到他
Wherever I find him,
无论是小胡同 还是廉价旅馆
whatever back alley or doss-house...
他都要给我列一个清单
there will always be a list.
他不可能在五分钟内 吸食这么多毒品
He couldn't have taken all that in the last five minutes.
他上飞机前 就已经嗑高了
He was high before he got on the plane.
他当时看上去可不像
He didn't seem high.
瘾君子最擅长伪装骗人了
Nobody deceives like an addict.
我不是瘾君子 我只是在利用毒品
I'm not an addict, I'm a user.
我这样来排解无聊
I alleviate boredom and
偶尔也用来加快思维进程
occasionally heighten my thought processes.
老天爷啊 这可是致命的
For God's sake! This could kill you!
- 你会死的 - 适量使用不会致命
- You could die! - Controlled usage is not usually fatal
何况禁欲也不会永生
and abstinence is not immortality.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
我在查艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
Emelia Ricoletti, I'm looking her up.
我们是该查一查
Oh, I suppose we should.
我有军情五处资料的最高访问权
I have access to the top level of the MI5 archive.
我已经进去查了
Yep, that's where I'm looking.
你觉得军情五处的保卫系统怎么样
What do you think of MI5 security?
我觉得设立保卫系统 这个点子不错
I think it would be a good idea.
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂 "悬案" 像他说的一样
Emelia Ricoletti, "Unsolved", like he says.
你们能不能安静一会儿 我得回去
Could you all just shut up for five minutes! I have to go back.
要不是你们跑上来乱叫
I was nearly there before
我马上就能解出来了
you stepped on and started yapping away!
"乱叫" 不好意思 是我们打断了你的思路吗
"Yapping?" Sorry, did we interrupt your session?
- 夏洛克 听我说 - 不听 你只会说个没完没了
- Sherlock, listen to me. - No, it only encourages you.
- 我没生你的气 - 那我真松了口气啊
- I'm not angry with you. - Oh, that's a relief!
我本来一直担心 不 等等 我其实并不担心
I was really worried... No, hold on, I really wasn't.
我曾经救过你
I was there for you before.
下一次我也会救你
I'll be there for you again.
我会一直守护着你
I'll always be there for you.
这都是我的错
This was my fault.
这事跟你没关系
It was nothing to do with you.
我应该想到 在监狱里的那一周
A week in a prison cell, I should have realised.
- 想到什么 - 对你来说
- Realised what? - That, in your case,
单独监禁是把你
solitary confinement is
和最强大的敌人 锁在了一起
locking you up with your worst enemy.
- 老天爷啊 - 吗啡还是可卡因
- Oh, for God's sake! - Morphine or cocaine?
- 你说什么 - 我什么都没说
- What did you say? - I didn't say anything.
不 你说了 你说
No, you did, you said...
今天又是哪种毒品 吗啡还是可卡因
Which is it today? Morphine or cocaine.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
吗啡还是可卡因 你今天用的哪种毒品
Morphine or cocaine... which is it today?
回答我 该死的
Answer me, damn it!
莫里亚蒂来过了
Moriarty was here.
莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty's dead.
- 我刚在飞机上 - 你说什么
- I was on a jet. - A what?
你和迈克罗夫特都在那里
You were there, and Mycroft.
你没离开过这个房间 福尔摩斯
You haven't left these rooms, Holmes.
你甚至动也没动过
You... haven't... moved.
好吧 告诉我 吗啡还是可卡因
Now, tell me, morphine or cocaine?
可卡因 浓度百分之七的溶液
Cocaine. A 7% solution.
- 你要来点吗 - 不要
- Would you care to try it? - No.
但是我倒是愿意把你
But I would quite like to find
所有的可卡因都找出来
every ounce of the stuff
然后倒出窗外去
in your possession and pour it out of the window.
那我得阻止你
I should be inclined to stop you.
那你会被强迫面对现实
Then you would be reminded, quite forcibly,
看清咱们俩谁是军人 谁又是瘾君子
which of us is a soldier and which of us a drug addict.
你不是军人 你是个医生
You're not a soldier, you are a doctor.
我是军医
I'm an army doctor,
也就是说我能边打碎
which means I could break
你身上的每一根骨头 一边说出它们的学名
every bone in your body while naming them.
亲爱的华生 你让情感蒙蔽了判断力
My dear Watson, you are allowing emotion to cloud your judgment.
绝不这么做
Never on a case.
你答应过我 绝不这么做的
You promised me, never on a case.
不 这只不过是 你故事中写的而已
No, I just said that in one of your stories.
听着 我乐意为了你装傻
Listen, I'm happy to play the fool for you.
如果你想 我会像个白痴一样 跟在你身后
I will run along behind you like some halfwit,
让你看上去更机智一些
making you look clever, if that's what you need.
但是老天爷啊 你得对自己 要求更高一些
But dear God above, you will hold yourself to a higher standard!
- 为什么 - 因为人们需要你这样做
- Why? - Because people need you to.
什么人 为什么 就因为你那些愚蠢的故事吗
What people, why? Because of your idiot stories?
是啊 就因为我那些愚蠢的故事
Yes, because of my "Idiot stories".
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
福尔摩斯先生 有电报 福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes, telegram, Mr. Holmes.
是什么 出什么事了
What is it? What's wrong?
- 是玛丽 - 玛丽 她怎么了
- It's Mary. - Mary? What about her?
- 她很有可能有危险 - 什么危险
- It's entirely possible she's in danger. - Danger?
- 没时间解释了 - 你是嗑高了 在说胡话吗
- There's not a moment to lose. - Is this the cocaine talking?
玛丽能有什么危险
What danger could Mary be in?
我确定她正和朋友在一起呢
I'm sure she's just visiting with friends.
快来
Come on!
发生了什么事 你神智还清醒吗
What is happening? Are you even in a fit state?
为了玛丽的事 当然了 别在这一点上怀疑我 华生
For Mary, of course. Never doubt that, Watson.
别再这么做了
Never that.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
我没事 我没事
I'm fine. I'm fine!
别戴那顶帽子
Not that one!
戴这顶帽子
This one.
- 为什么 - 你是夏洛克·福尔摩斯 戴你该戴的帽子
- Why? - You're Sherlock Holmes. Wear the damn hat.
马车 马车
Cab! Cab!
告诉我 她在哪里
So tell me, where is she?
你必须告诉我 发生了什么事情
You must tell me, what's going on?!
老好人华生
Oh, good old Watson!
你不问点问题 咱们还真没事干啊
How would we fill the time if you didn't ask questions?!
夏洛克 快说我老婆在哪里 混蛋
Sherlock, tell me where my bloody wife is, you pompous prick,
不然我就揍得你两眼发黑
or I'll punch your lights out!
福尔摩斯 她在哪里
Holmes, where is she?
她在一座废弃的教堂里
A de-sanctified church.
她觉得自己发现了解决办法
She thinks she's found the solution and,
就因为这个原因
for no better reason than that,
她将自己置身于 巨大的危机中
she's put herself in the path of considerable danger.
你真是选了个好老婆啊
What an excellent choice of wife.
真是见鬼了
What the devil?!
我找到她们了
I've found them.
- 这是什么情况 玛丽 - 这是整件事的核心 约翰
- What is all this, Mary? - This is the heart of it all, John.
这是整个阴谋的关键
The heart of the conspiracy.
天啊 这是什么地方
Great God, what is this place?
你到底在这里做什么
And what the devil are you doing here?!
我一直在做调查
I've been making enquiries.
福尔摩斯先生让我做的
Mr. Holmes asked me.
福尔摩斯 你怎么能这样做
Holmes, how could you?
不是他 是更聪明那个福尔摩斯
No, not him, the clever one.
我觉得很明显
It seemed obvious to me
这件事情不可能是独自策划的
that this business could not be managed alone.
我认为瑞克莱蒂太太有帮手
My theory is that Mrs. Ricoletti had help.
她的朋友在帮她
Help from her friends.
真精彩 玛丽 "更聪明的那位福尔摩斯"
Bravo, Mary. "The clever one?"
我 我以为要失去你了
I... I thought I was losing you.
我以为我们一直在
I thought perhaps we were...
- 忽视彼此 - 是你要搬出去的
- neglecting each other. - Well, you're the one who moved out.
我在跟玛丽说话
I was talking to Mary.
你在替迈克罗夫特工作吗
You're working for Mycroft?
他想监视这位疯狂的兄弟
He likes to keep an eye on his mad sibling.
手边还有个间谍做任务 你没发现
And he had a spy to hand. Has it never occurred to you
你妻子作为一个护士 有点太能干了吗
your wife is excessively skilled for a nurse?
当然没发现 因为他知道护士的能力所在
Of course it hasn't, because he knows what a nurse is capable of.
- 你什么时候开始这么想的 - 就刚刚
- When did it occur to you? - Only now, I'm afraid.
作为一个反应慢的小弟弟 你一定过得很辛苦吧
Must be difficult, being the slow little brother.
真是不堪回首 我们说得够多了 还是集中注意力吧
Time I sped up. Enough chatter, let's concentrate.
你说得对 这是怎么回事
Yes, all right. What's all this about?
他们要干什么
What do they want to accomplish?
我们为何不走近弄个明白
Why don't we go and find out.
抱歉 我见锣就想敲
Sorry! I can never resist a gong.
- 见到闹剧 就想插一脚 - 真是没想到
- Or a touch of the dramatic. - Never have guessed!
虽然在这方面 你们好像跟我一样热情
Though it seems you share my enthusiasm in that regard.
棒极了
Excellent.
顶级的剧场
Superlative theatre.
我真是欣赏这场面
I applaud the spectacle.
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂饮弹自尽
Emelia Ricoletti shot herself,
然后死而复生 谋杀了她的丈夫
then apparently returned from the grave and killed her husband.
所以
So...
她是怎么做到的
how was it done?
我们来按顺序理清一下真相吧
Let's take the events in order.
瑞克莱蒂夫人用
Mrs. Ricoletti gets
非常有效的方式 吸引了所有人的注意
everyone's attention in very efficient fashion.
是你
You!
是你吗
You?!
还是我
Or me?
她把一只手枪放进嘴里
She places one of the revolvers in her mouth,
实际上开火的 是另一只口朝下的枪
while actually firing the other into the ground.
她的同伙在窗帘上撒上了血液
An accomplice sprays the curtains with blood
因此楼下受惊的人们
and thus her apparent suicide
就都目击到了她的自杀
is witnessed by the frightened crowd below.
一具跟瑞克莱蒂太太十分相似的
A substitute corpse,
尸体取而代之出现在了她的位置
bearing a strong resemblance to Mrs. Ricoletti
并随后被送去了太平间
takes her place and is later transported to the morgue,
这对于苏格兰警察来说
a grubby little suicide
只是毫无兴趣的小自杀案
of little interest to Scotland Yard.
同时 真正的瑞克莱蒂夫人溜走了
Meanwhile, the real Mrs. Ricoletti slips away.
然后就到了十分聪明的环节了
Now comes the really clever part.
瑞克莱蒂夫人说服了
Mrs. Ricoletti persuaded a cab driver,
一位认识她的马车夫
someone who knew her,
在她丈夫最喜欢去的鸦片馆外截住了他
to intercept her husband outside his favourite opium den.
那里是上演一场绝妙闹剧的最佳舞台
The perfect stage for a perfect drama.
你是谁 你想做什么
Who are you? What do you want?
艾美莉亚
Emelia?
救命
Help!
完美的身份认证
A perfect positive identification.
瑞克莱蒂夫人死而复生
The late Mrs. Ricoletti has returned from the grave
加上高超的装扮
and a little skilled make-up
就塑造出了复仇怨灵的熊熊怒火
and you have nothing less than the wrath of a vengeful ghost.
最后只剩下一件事
There was only one thing left to do.
快点动手 你不必感到难过
Swiftly now. No tears.
最后只需将真的瑞克莱蒂夫人
All that remained was to substitute the real Mrs. Ricoletti
替换掉太平间里的假尸体就行了
for the corpse in the morgue.
这下 就算有人想要验尸
This time, should anyone attempt to identify her,
那也毫无疑问的就是她了
it would be positively, absolutely her.
但她为什么要这么做
But why would she do that?
为了证明观点而去死吗
Die to prove a point?
所有的伟业都有殉道者
Every great cause has martyrs.
所有战争都需要牺牲 没错 这就是一场战争
Every war has suicide missions and make no mistake, this is war.
半数的人类正在与另外半数交战
One half of the human race at war with the other.
一支近在咫尺的无形军队
The invisible army hovering at our elbow,
照料着我们的家园
tending to our homes,
养育着我们的孩子
raising our children.
他们却被忽视着 被轻视着
Ignored, patronised,
被蔑视着
disregarded.
甚至不允许有投票的权利
Not allowed so much as a vote.
然而这毕竟是支军队
But an army nonetheless,
她们已经为了崇高的伟业而崛起
ready to rise up in the best of causes.
纠正人类有史以来就固存的不公
To put right an injustice as old as humanity itself.
华生 你看 迈克罗夫特说得对
So you see, Watson, Mycroft was right.
这是一场我们必定会输的战争
This is a war we must lose.
她已经病入膏肓了
She was dying.
- 谁 - 艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
- Who was? - Emelia Ricoletti.
她有明显的肺病症状
There were clear signs of consumption...
她应该不久于世了
I doubt she wasn't long for this world.
所以她决定让自己死得其所
So she decided to make her death count.
她对美国的秘密社交圈很熟悉
She was already familiar with the secret societies of America.
并且她有办法
And was able to draw on their methods of fear
公开敞亮地进行威胁恐吓
and intimidation to publicly, very publicly,
逼尤斯塔斯·卡迈克尔爵士 直面他犯下的罪恶
confront Sir Eustace Carmichael with the sins of his past.
他在美国就认识她了
He knew her out in the States.
许诺给她一切
Promised her everything.
婚姻 地位
Marriage, position.
之后他不过是玩弄她
And then he had his way with her...
抛弃她
and threw her over.
留她一人 身无分文
Left her abandoned and penniless.
霍珀
Hooper!
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
郑重声明 福尔摩斯 她可没骗过我
For the record, Holmes, she didn't have me fooled.
为什么你从不提及我 先生
Why do you never mention me, sir?
艾美莉亚以为 和瑞克莱蒂在一起就能幸福
Emelia thought that she'd found happiness with Ricoletti,
但他也是个畜生
but he was a brute too.
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂是我们的朋友
Emelia Ricoletti was our friend.
你根本想不到 那个混账如何对待她
You have no idea how that bastard treated her.
但新娘呢 福尔摩斯 我们看到过她的
But the Bride, Holmes, we saw her.
没错 华生 我们看到过
Yes, Watson, we did.
那个碎玻璃的声音吗
The sound of breaking glass?
当时碎的不是窗户
Not a window,
这不过是古老的戏剧诡计
just an old theatrical trick.
- 这不可能是真的 福尔摩斯 - 是不可能
- It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot! - No, it can't.
那叫做佩珀尔幻象
It's called Pepper's Ghost.
在镜中反射出活人的身影
A simple reflection in glass of a living, breathing person.
他们唯一的纰漏 就是弄碎了玻璃
Their only mistake was breaking the glass when they removed it.'
看看四周
Look around you.
房间里全是新娘
This room is full of brides.
一旦她站出来
Once she had risen,
任何人都能成为她
anyone could be her.
复仇的鬼魂
The avenging ghost.
是一个让心怀恶意的男人
A legend to strike terror into the heart of any man
恐惧不已的传说
with malicious intent.
一个追踪没有得到恶报的混蛋
A spectre to stalk those unpunished brutes
要与之清算过去的幽灵
whose reckoning is long overdue.
复仇女神觉醒了
A league of furies awakened.
那位我
The women I...
我们 欺骗过背叛过的女人
WE have lied to, betrayed.
我们忽视和蔑视的女人
The women we have ignored and disparaged.
一旦产生了这样的想法
Once the idea exists,
就难很消除了
it cannot be killed.
一个目标坚定的人才能做到这样
This is the work of a single-minded person.
她还非常了解 尤斯塔斯爵士的精神虐待
Someone who knew first-hand about Sir Eustace's mental cruelty.
了解他阴暗的秘密
The dark secret,
这只有她最好的朋友才知道
kept from all but her closest friends,
包括艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂
including Emelia Ricoletti...
这位曾多年前遭受丈夫虐待的女人
the woman her husband wronged all those years before.
如果忽略鬼魂
If one disregards the ghost,
那就只有一个嫌疑人了
there is only one suspect.
是吧 卡迈克尔夫人
Isn't that right, Lady Carmichael?
但还有个小地方 我不太明白
One small detail doesn't quite make sense to me, however.
为什么要找我来阻止
Why engage me to prevent
这件你打算实施的谋杀
a murder you intended to commit?
"我不太明白 不应该是这样啊"
"Doesn't quite make sense, doesn't quite make sense."
你当然不明白 因为这不是真的
Of course it doesn't make sense, it's not real.
夏洛克
Oh, Sherlock.
躲猫猫
Peek-a-boo.
不
No.
不 不是你
No, not you.
不可能是你
It can't be you.
得了吧 好好想想
I mean, come on, be serious.
服装 锣
The costumes, the gong?
作为一个超级反派
Speaking as a criminal mastermind,
我们并没有真的锣 或者特殊的服装
we don't really have gongs or special outfits.
这到底是怎么回事
What the hell is going on?
这对你来说够蠢吗
Is this silly enough for you yet?
哥特风够浓吗 够疯狂吗 即使对你而言
Gothic enough? Mad enough, even for you?
你想不明白 夏洛克 是因为这不是真的
It doesn't make sense, Sherlock, because it's not real.
- 一切都不是真的 - 他在说什么
- None of it. - What's he talking about?
这些都是你的幻想
This is all in your mind.
夏洛克
Sherlock?
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
你在做梦
You're dreaming.
他在做梦吗
Is he dreaming?
他醒了
And there he is.
我们还以为 你要死了呢
Thought we'd lost you for a moment.
容我问一下 这就是你说的"控制用量"吗
May I just check, is this what you mean by "Controlled usage"?
艾美莉亚·瑞克莱蒂太太 告诉我她埋在哪里
Mrs. Emelia Ricoletti, I need to know where she was buried.
- 一百二十年前被埋在哪里吗 - 是的
- What, 120 years ago? - Yes.
如果还有记录 也得花几周时间来查
That would take weeks to find, if those records even exists.
- 即使是动用我的资源 - 查到了
- Even with my resources. - Got it.
我不明白 这一切有什么关联
I don't get it, how is this relevant?
我要知道自己是对的 然后我才能肯定
I need to know I was right, then I'll be sure.
- 你是说莫里亚蒂怎么做到的 - 没错
- You mean how Moriarty did it? - Yes.
但这些都不是真实发生的 是你自己想的
But none of that really happened, it was in your head.
我的调查是幻想中的
My investigation was the fantasy,
但犯罪方式和我的解释一样
the crime happened exactly as I explained.
墓碑是她朋友们立的
The stone was erected by a group of her friends.
你想在这里找什么
I don't know what you think you'll find here.
我得试试
I need to try!
瑞克莱蒂太太被埋在这里
Mrs. Ricoletti was buried here,
但另一具尸体呢
but what happened to the other one?
在那场所谓的自杀后 代替她的尸体
The corpse they substituted for her after the so-called suicide?
- 他们肯定搬走了 - 但搬到哪里去了
- They'd move it, of course they would. - But where?
反正不在这里
Well, not here.
但他们肯定会这么做
But that... That's exactly what they must have done.
同谋者都是有内应的
The conspirators had someone on the inside.
他们找到一具尸体
They found a body, just
就像莫莉·霍珀给我找了具尸体
like Molly Hooper found a body for me, when...
我们不用再说一遍那件事了 对吧
Yeah, well, we don't need to go into all that again, do we?
你不是真的要这样做吧
You're not seriously going to do this?
我们就是为这个来的 我需要答案
It's why we came here. I need to know.
简直是瘾君子的口吻
Spoken like an addict.
- 这对我来说很重要 - 不 这说明你得接受治疗
- This is important to me! - No, this is you needing a fix.
- 约翰 - 莫里亚蒂回来了
- John... - Moriarty's back.
我们有案子 真实生活中 我们有问题需要解决
We have a case, we have a real-life problem right now.
等一下就解决它 先让我把这事做完
Getting to that, it's next on the list. Just let me do this.
不行 大家总是让你为所欲为
No, everyone always lets you do whatever you want.
- 所以你才变成现在这样 - 约翰 拜托
- That's how you got in this state! - John, please...
这次我不奉陪了 夏洛克 再也不了
I'm not playing this time, Sherlock. Not any more!
等你准备好工作了 再给我打电话
When you're ready to go to work, give me a call.
- 我要带玛丽回家了 - 你说什么
- I'm taking Mary home. - You're what?
- 玛丽要带我回家了 - 这还差不多
- Mary's taking me home. - Better.
- 他说得对 - 那又怎样
- He's right, you know. - So what if he's right?!
他总是对的 这太无聊了
He's always right, it's boring!
你会帮我吗
Will you help me?
找出那个女人
Cherchez la femme.
上帝啊
Oh, dear.
这里已经囊空如洗了
The cupboard is bare.
他们肯定把她埋在下面了
They must have buried it underneath.
肯定埋在棺材下面了
They must have buried it underneath the coffin.
你运气不好啊 夏洛克
Bad luck, Sherlock.
或许他们用其他方式处理了尸体
Maybe they got rid of the body in another way.
- 不 - 很有可能
- No... - More than likely.
毕竟这是很久以前的事了
At any rate, it was a very long time ago.
我们眼下还有
We do have slightly more
更紧迫的事要办 弟弟
pressing matters to hand, little brother.
莫里亚蒂 死而复生
Moriarty? Back from the dead?
勿忘我
Do not forget me.
Do not forget me!
这里
This?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
我还是没醒 对吧
Still not awake, am I?
太深了 夏洛克 你陷得太深了
Too deep, Sherlock, way too deep.
恭喜你 将会成为有史以来第一位
Congratulations, you will be the first man in history
埋在自己思维殿堂里的人
to be buried in his own Mind Palace.
这场景也太夸张了 你不觉得吗
The setting is a shade melodramatic, don't you think?
对你我而言
For you and me?
一点都不夸张
Not at all.
你到底是什么东西
What are you?
你知道我是什么东西
You know what I am.
我是莫里亚蒂
I'm Moriarty.
犯罪界的拿破仑
The Napoleon of Crime.
- 莫里亚蒂已经死了 - 在你脑中可没有
- Moriarty's dead! - Not in your mind.
我在你的脑海里永存
I'll never be dead there.
你曾把自己的大脑称为硬盘
You once called your brain a hard drive.
现在 和病毒打声招呼吧
Well, say hello to the virus.
这就是我们的结局
This is how we end, you and I.
永远在这里
Always here,
永远都在一起
always together.
你的想法很棒 莫里亚蒂
You have a magnificent brain, Moriarty.
我很佩服
I admire it.
我承认或许 它能和我的大脑相提并论
I concede it may even be the equal of my own.
我很感动
I'm touched.
我很荣幸
I'm honoured.
但说到在悬崖边上
But when it comes to the matter of unarmed combat
徒手格斗
on the edge of a precipice...
你只有落水的份
you're going in the water,
小个子
short-arse.
你觉得自己很高大勇猛吗 夏洛克
Oh, you think you're so big and strong, Sherlock!
我可不敢苟同
Not with me.
我就是你的弱点
I am your weakness!
我能打倒你
I keep you down!
你的每一次跌倒 失败
Every time you stumble, every time you fail,
每一次的弱势
when you're weak,
我都
I... am...
在那里
there!
不
No,
你别再试着抵抗了
don't try to fight it.
躺好认输吧
Lie back and lose!
我们一起跳下去吧
Shall we go over together?
必须是一起跳 对吧
It has to be together, doesn't it?
最终 永远都是
At the end it's always just you
你和我
and me!
教授 麻烦你离我的朋友远一点
Professor, if you wouldn't mind stepping away from my friend,
我相信 他很讨厌你的行为
I do believe he finds your attention a shade annoying.
这不公平 你们有两个人
That's not fair, there's two of you!
我们一直是两个人 你没看过斯特兰德报吗
There's always two of us. Don't you read The Strand?
跪下 教授
On your knees, Professor.
把手放到头上
Hands behind your head.
谢谢你 约翰
Thank you, John.
你什么时候开始叫我约翰了
Since when do you call me John?
生活处处充满惊喜
You'd be surprised.
那倒未必
No, I wouldn't.
该醒来了 夏洛克
Time you woke up, Sherlock.
我是写故事的人 我知道自己在哪里
I'm a story-teller, I know when I'm in one.
当然
Of course.
你当然知道 约翰
Of course you do, John.
那他长什么样
So what's he like?
另一个世界的我
The other me in the other place?
比他看上去更聪明
Smarter than he looks.
那肯定是聪明绝顶了
Pretty damn smart, then.
是 聪明绝顶
Pretty damn smart.
天啊 你俩干脆直接私奔吧
Ugh, why don't you two just elope, for God's sake?!
你真是粗鲁
Impertinent.
你真是无礼
Offensive.
介意我来吗
Actually, would you mind?
一点也不
Not at all.
- 总算轮到我了 - 是啊
- It was my turn. - Quite so.
你打算怎么醒过来
So how do you plan to wake up?
我觉得应该这样做
I should think like this.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
只限于我们之间的秘密 约翰 坠落是杀不死我的
Between you and me, John, I always survive a fall.
可你怎么做到的
But how?
很简单 亲爱的华生
Elementary, my dear Watson.
- 想我了吗 - 夏洛克 你还好吗
- Miss me? - Sherlock, are you all right?
当然 我为什么不好
Yes. Of course I am, why wouldn't I be?
因为你可能服药过量 你应该去医院
Because you probably just OD'd. You should be in hospital.
没时间了
Hm, no time.
我现在得去贝克街 莫里亚蒂回来了
I have to go to Baker Street now, Moriarty's back.
我倒是希望他回来了
I almost hope he is,
如果这能让你不再沉浸于此
if it'll save you from this.
现在不需要这个了 我有正事要办
No need for that now, I've got the real thing.
- 我有工作要做 - 夏洛克
- I have work to do. - Sherlock...
答应我
promise me.
你还站在这里干什么
What are you still doing here?
你快帮我弄个赦免令什么的啊
Shouldn't you be off getting me a pardon or something,
像个大哥该有的样子
like a proper big brother?
华生医生
Dr. Watson...
照顾好他
Look after him.
拜托了
Please.
夏洛克 等等 解释一下 莫里亚蒂还活着吗
Sherlock, hang on, explain. Moriarty's alive, then?
我没说他还活着 我是说他回来了
I never said he was alive, I said he was back.
那他死了吗
So he's dead?
他当然死了
Of course he's dead, he
他脑袋都开花了 不可能活下来
blew his own brains out, no-one survives that.
我刚为了证明这一点 还服药过量了
I just went to the trouble of an overdose to prove it.
莫里亚蒂死了 这毋庸置疑
Moriarty is dead, no question.
但重要的是 我很清楚他接下来 要做什么事情
But more importantly, I know exactly what he's going to do next.
航空器
Flying machines,
还有什么 电话工具
these, er, telephone contraptions?
都是些什么疯狂的幻想啊
What sort of lunatic fantasy is that?
这只是我对
It was simply my conjecture
未来世界
of what a future world might look like
还有你和我在其中的猜测
and how you and I might fit inside it.
逻辑学家能从一滴掉落的水珠
From a drop of water a logician should be able to infer
推测出它是来自大西洋 还是尼亚加拉河
the possibility of an Atlantic or a Niagara.
或者是莱辛巴赫瀑布
Or a Reichenbach?
这件你极度重视的案子 写好了吗
Have you written up your account of the case?
当然
Yes.
修改后是我罕见未能破获的案子 对吧
Modified to put it down as one of my rare failures, of course?
是的
Of course.
隐形军队的
The Adventure Of...
大冒险
The Invisible Army.
复仇女神
The League Of Furies?
还是恐怖军团
The Monstrous Regiment?
我更喜欢可恶的新娘
I rather thought The Abominable Bride.
有点骇人听闻
A trifle lurid.
但肯定畅销 它里面还有谋杀呢
It'll sell. It's got proper murders in it too.
你是专家嘛
You're the expert.
至于你的故事
As for your own tale,
你确定只用了百分之七的溶液吗
are you sure it's still just a 7% solution that you take?
我认为你可能加大了剂量
I think you may have increased the dosage.
或许我想象力太丰富了
Perhaps I was being a little fanciful.
但或许这些事真的会实现
But perhaps such things could come to pass.
无论如何 我相信自己 会很适应那个世界
In any case, I know I would be very much at home in such a world.
- 我不认为我能 - 我可不这样认为
- Huh, I don't think I would be. - I beg to differ.
但我一直知道自己 是超越时代的人
But then I've always known I was a man out of his time.